<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true trauaile of all faithfull Christians, hovve to escape the daungers of the vvicked vvorld VVhereunto is added a christian exercise for priuate housholders.</title>
            <author>Chub, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117145</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852360</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852360</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17676</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18707)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17676)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 879:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true trauaile of all faithfull Christians, hovve to escape the daungers of the vvicked vvorld VVhereunto is added a christian exercise for priuate housholders.</title>
                  <author>Chub, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[144] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Charlewood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: W. Chub.</note>
                  <note>"A christian exercise for priuate housholders" has caption title and separate register.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G H⁴; A B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE True trauaile of all faithfull Chriſtians, howe to eſcape the daungers of this <hi>vvicked vvorld.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhereunto is added a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an exerciſe for priuate housholders.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HEBR. 12.1.2.</bibl>
               <p>Wherefore let vs alſo ſeeing that we are compaſſed with ſo great a clowde of witneſſes, caſt away euery thing that preſſeth downe, &amp; the ſinne that han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſo faſt on. Let vs run with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the race that is ſet before vs, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto Ieſus the autor and finiſher of our faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at London, by Iohn Charlewood. 1585.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull Ma. Iohn Thinne Eſquier, his very good Patrone and Maſter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He continuall fauoure I haue found at your han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des (right worshipfull) eſpecially of late in Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don, as well hy writing as by your perſonall trauel, doth charge my minde with ſo many gnawing co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, that I can neuer expreſſe a ſufficient thankfulnes, nor render ſome token of a partepay, ſuch is the hardnes of my happe and the straightnes of pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent time, that nowe I can not match wishing with wyll, nor ſufficiency with deſire. How be it, I yeelde my ſelfe to your accuſtomed acceptation, and my hope which shalbe a pledge <hi>de attica fide,</hi> do I bequeath vnto future time. I holde you ſo firme my good freende, that notwithſtanding the ſubtiltye of interceptors, you ſtand vngaged, to my no ſmall comfort, wherefore ſeeing
<pb facs="tcp:17676:3"/> I haue no thankfull ſignification of good wyll, I preſent vnto your worship a portion of my profeſsion, not as a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient workmanship for your worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but as a token of my grateful mind It is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and therefore the vntimely hatching may bring foorth ſickly Byrds. But I humbly beſeech you worship that as you are already patrone of my poore liuing, ſo you will freendly allowe of the patronage of my ſelfe, &amp; this my ſlender worke, and ſo I shall not onely be ſo much beholding to you as proceſſe of time cannot weare away the remembrance, but euermore bound in harty prayers that the Lorde may proſper your affayres, and daily bleſſe your ſelfe and all yours to whoſe merci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full tuition I commend you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded during life moſt faithfull</hi> W. Chub.</signed> 
               <dateline>From <hi>Zelwoode</hi> 
                  <date>the <hi>8.</hi> of September.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:3"/>
            <head>To the godly Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F a man ſhoulde ſit ſtil but a litle while and behold this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent laſt age of the worlde, and viewe the contents of this time,<note place="margin">Cataſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phe.</note> and pawſe vpon it with indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent reaſon. It would in a maner amaze a well ſetled minde to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. But if one ſhold ſit in an open place, wher there is daily concourſe to and froe of great multitudes, and ſhould ſcarſe ſee one ſound and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite man to paſſe by, would you not thinke it were a crippelled worlde? and that they hadde beene among mighty enimies in a daungerous skyrmiſh? Surely if we conſider the whole parts of a man, and weigh in conſcience that he ſhould conſiſt of godlines, reaſon, and vertue, and do find that either the ſpirituall aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, or the worldly conſort, hath
<pb facs="tcp:17676:4"/> ſo grappled &amp; battelled, that ſome are become Heteroclites, and ſome Monſters. It is a very hard thing in this laſt age to finde a ſound and perfit man, but that in one or other of theſe former partes hee ſeemeth to haue a defect, and that is percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the common ſociety of man. For wherin wee ought to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate one with the other in godly exerciſes and heauenly councell we iarre, we vary, we diſdaine, we enuy, backbite, and ſlaunder one an other yea of the ſame profeſsion and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as though we were ſtraungers to each other, and fauters to our ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſaries, and I haue founde them moſt buſie to ſpeake behinde a mans backe, that haue had neuer a worde to his face, nay neuer a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but by heereſay and ſurmiſe. I ſorrow to heare it, I ſigh to knowe it, and I deſire God to amend it, for I dreade me in theſe daies in the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Roſe is ſoneſt found a Canker.</p>
            <p>Reaſon that in times paſt hath
<pb facs="tcp:17676:4"/> beene taken for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the common wealth, and a gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour as well of naturall as of morall yea and oeconomicall matters, and hath beene diſtributed into diuers degrees for their direction, and in all ſortes of people ſhe hath beene ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced to the higheſt woman, and without the which, neither the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of a common wealth hath beene any thing worth at all, neither with out it hath man beene eſteemed as a man, now ſhe is abaſed like and old ſchoolemaſter that hath taught ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good ſchollers, in the ende com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to teache one the poore A. B. C. For whereas ſhee hath beene a publique teacher of all men, both for counſell, comfort, and helpe, nowe ſhe teacheth men to looke to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and if they will be wiſe, to loue their owne ſelues, and to care for their owne ſelues, in ſo much, that all her ſchollers are become in a manner ſingular fellowes, neither imparting to others, neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating
<pb facs="tcp:17676:5"/> with others, and yet it is a lamentable matter to ſee thoſe whom they ſo councell, if they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe it, they are nowe called ſnud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and pigges, that erewhile were called beggers and bankrupts.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uo tene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vultus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tantem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tea no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> A pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull worlde, to ſee ſuch a forcible doctrine, where is the lawe of God, which commaundeth all not one? <hi>Loue God, and thy neighbour as thy ſelf</hi> where is the Law of nature? which giueth generall commaundement, <hi>Fac aliis fieri quod cupis ipſe tibi.</hi> Doe to others as thou wouldeſt be done vnto. Where is S. Paules counſel? <hi>Doo good vnto all men,</hi> VVhat is there become of Tullies ſentence? <hi>Non nobis ſed patriae nati ſumus.</hi> wee are not borne for our ſelues but for our Country. In times paſt, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was accounted of, at this time wealth &amp; they that haue it, be they neuer neuer ſo bare and baſe ſerue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges are beſt eſteemed, the time may come, that a man may bee had in reputation, in meane tyme, Gods
<pb facs="tcp:17676:5"/> wyll be doone, <hi>et caetera infinita.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine if wee beholde vertue conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her noble beauty and ſhape, &amp; that ſhe was a ſinguler braunch and member to ſette foorth and adorne man, howe ſhe is now diſfigured, &amp; diſmembred and defaced with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite actions of vice, it is pittifull to ſee that her ornaments, namely Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, temperancy, chaſtity, equity, trueth, pitty, charity and ſuch like &amp;c. are quite cut of, and the twigges little eſteemed. I feare me where the mighty boughes are ſo often and ſo vnſeaſonably cut of, in the ende, they will hazard the whole tree and ſtocke, God of his mercye preſerue his little flocke.</p>
            <p>For thy better preſeruation (good Reader) I haue heere compoſed a ſmall peece of worke,<note place="margin">The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> in the which I haue breefely layd downe the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſuruey of a Chriſtian. And firſt he ſhall ſee himſelfe what he is naturally, what ſin reigneth in him. How it is nouriſhed, howe many
<pb facs="tcp:17676:6"/> greeuous enimies he hath by reaſon of ſin, laſt of all the eaſe and remedy he hath againſt the force of ſinne. VVhich I haue doone, the rather becauſe I ſee a great many Trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in opinions, and ſome ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rech themſelues, and ſome ouerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor them ſelues, which is more for want of wit, then for lacke of wyl. And for that I pitty their weary &amp; vnprofitable trauell, doo in Chriſtes name inuite them to this Harbour, as the beſt preparation I haue for mine owne part to entertaine them, beſeeching the Lorde to giue them knowledge, iudgement, and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry deſire. It is but ſhortly compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, becauſe it ſhall not bee loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and chargable vnto thee gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader, a ſmall almes is inough for this hard world. Reade it ouer with diſcretion, and where thou findeſt any thing toothſome, take it as thankfully, as I beſtow it hartily, and if thou hap with any groſſe or vnſauerye matter, paſſe it ouer as
<pb facs="tcp:17676:6"/> freendly as I ſhall take it ſorrowful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and if thou be one of them that loue me, thou wilt take it howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be, in good part, but if thou be one of them that of late condemned me of Idlenes, <hi>I</hi> ſorrow no more to be ſlaundered, then thou doſt ſhame to be deceiued, and yet as charitye bindeth mee, <hi>I</hi> wyll pray for thee, and byd thee hartily farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:7"/>
            <head>Autor calumniatoribus.</head>
            <l>NOn ego conticui, iacui ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> deſidioſe,</l>
            <l>lingua licit fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uit penna locuta fuit:</l>
            <l>Nec me delituiſſe putes, reticente talentum,</l>
            <l>En patet officii, cura, laborque mei</l>
            <l>Fatur, et in ſeculum conſcriptus ſermo perenne</l>
            <l>Viuit, et in longa poſteritate manet.</l>
            <l>Vade liber, cauſa domini, damnabere forſan:</l>
            <l>Sed quos, ſunt docti, conſulit ille prius</l>
            <l>Inuidiat, pro me, vel ſi te nauſeat vllus</l>
            <l>Dic, ſibi quod nullum ſcripſerat autor opus</l>
            <l>Sim licet indoctus, tibi dico perlege, diſce</l>
            <l>te<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> monere mouet me, tua cauſa, lege</l>
            <l>Meué alios legito ſi fit tibi cura ſalutis</l>
            <l>Sera niſi capiat te Metanaea nimis.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </l>
            <l>Plurima nam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> fluunt totum peccata per orbem</l>
            <l>et genus humanum crimine polluitur.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>VV. Ch.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:7"/>
            <head>What man is.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ith it is, and hath béene alwayes the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of man,<note place="margin">Cap. 1.</note> to know things naturall what they are, what opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, vertues, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes procéedeth from them, and to what purpoſe euery thing is ordeyned, and thereby dooth beſt ſéeke for thoſe thinges that are neceſſary, and auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thoſe thinges that are hurtfull, and meaſureth his knowledge by times &amp; ſeaſons fitteſt for his purpoſe, by the which hee hath looked ſo into the bowels of naturall thinges, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt no faculty wanteth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowledge, wherein he hath a delight, either for the preſeruation of his body from noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome thinges, or his eſtate from pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. He knoweth the diſpoſition of the heauens, the yéelding of the earth, the vertue of the one, and the beſt ſeaſon of
<pb facs="tcp:17676:8"/> the other, neyther is there a corner of the heauens, or of the earth, or of the ſeas left vnſerched, as for example. The Aſtronomer fléeth to heauen, and ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his ſkyl. The Huſbandman ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the earth, and ſheweth hys ſkyll. The Marryner the Seas, and likewiſe ſheweth his ſkyll. Euery Artificer on the earth profiteth his ſkyll, with an encreaſing knowledge, and as touching the eſtate of our bodyes euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that knowledge to preſerue it both in helth and alſo in proſperity, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to natures expectation. But aboue all theſe knowledges, me thinke I ſee not man to runne ſo néere home as to knowe himſelfe whereof he is made, what procéedeth naturally from him, and wherefore hée is made, howe hee is compaſſed about with many calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and miſeries, and how death dooth followe him ſtep by ſtep, whether ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he goeth. A thing to be deſired by the Heathens example, who ſayd <hi>Noſce teipſum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8. Pſal. 144.4.</note> Likewiſe by the good prophet Dauid, who ſaid, <hi>VVhat is man that &amp;c.</hi> and that he may be the better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted héerewith, conferring it wyth
<pb facs="tcp:17676:8"/> hys owne eſtate, I wyll lay downe the opinion of our aunceſters, who wyth experience and knowledge, haue gyuen vs a true light thereof. The Hebrewes deſcribed man wholy by thrée proper names that were giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him which in the Bible, eſpecially in the Pſalmes are founde in many places, that is <hi>Ish, Enosh, Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Three names giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to man.</note> which according to the true interpretation of the wordes, and true meaning of the writers, I wyll lay downe, the rather that by them (as by a bréefe table) wee may not onely quickly ſuruey our eſtate, but excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Calender in our myndes, the true proportion of our ſelues, and I wyll deſcribe the ſignification of them, as they are and firſt with <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam</hi> is a name of ſignification giuen to our firſt parent Adam, not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly properly to be called by it, but by ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification to witnes as wel to himſelfe as to all his poſterity, what God ment by it, and doth ſignifie Red earth, which name doth put vs in remembraunce of what ſubſtaunce we be of, and whereof we be created, that is, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verye brittle
<pb facs="tcp:17676:9"/> earth, according to Gods owne ſaying, <hi>Earth thou art, and to earth thou ſhalt returne againe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen.</note> and this chaunge is not attributed to one man, or to one nation but vnto all people in the worlde, of what eſtate or degrée ſoeuer. As appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth well by the Hiſtory of <hi>Zerxes,</hi> who had a very great Armye of Souldiers, and as he marched on the ſide of an hill looking back on his great hoſte, did not glory in them, but receiued a ſuddaine motion, and therewithall wept, hys vncle <hi>Artabanus</hi> béeing preſent, and ſéeing ſo ſuddaine a chaunge, demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the cauſe, to whom he aunſwered, now I record in my minde, how ſhorte the life of man is, when of this greate multitude after and hundred yéeres not one of theſe ſhall remaine aliue. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race</hi> ſayth, <hi>Quo pius Eneas, quo Tullus diues, et Ancus, puluis et vmbra ſumus.</hi> Whether are thoſe Kinges gone, the godly <hi>Eneas,</hi> rich <hi>Tullus,</hi> and <hi>Ancus?</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is made, we are but duſt and as a ſhaddow. The prophet crying out vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to all the world, dooth ſpeake vnto man kinde, <hi>O earth, earth, earth,</hi> now vpon this true certificate of our ſubſtaunce,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:9"/> we are to learne thrée good conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>1.</hi> The frailty of our ſubſtaunce:<note place="margin">Three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> 
               <hi>2.</hi> What fruite it yéeldeth. <hi>3.</hi> Thirdly what regard we ſhould haue to it. As touching the frailty of man in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſubſtaunce; we ſe by the courſe of his time, is but ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, as Iob ſayth,<note place="margin">Iob. 14.5.</note> 
               <hi>He hath but a ſhort time to liue, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vp like a flower, and ſuddainly is cut downe.</hi> Likewiſe, in the <hi>39.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 39.6.7.</note> Pſal. <hi>Beholde thou haſt made my dayes as it were a ſpan long, and mine age is euen as nothing, in reſpect of thee, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily euery man lyuing is altogether va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, for man walketh in a vaine ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and diſquieteth himſelfe in vaine &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> did expreſſe this frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie when newes came vnto him that his ſonne was dead, he aunſwered. <hi>Scio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me mortalem eum genuiſse.</hi> I know that I my ſelfe being a mortall man did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get him. So that in all ages and times we haue ſeene, that all ſorts of people haue vayled theyr chéefeſt top ſayle vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, &amp; haue ſhewed that they haue had no ſtrength at all to ſtriue againſt him. In conſideration whereof, let vs goe farder &amp; ſée the ſecond poynt, which is,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:10"/> what fruite this frailnes yéeldeth. As we haue prooued the very ſubſtaunce of man to be but earth,<note place="margin">2. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> ſo let vs conſider that the very earth of it ſelfe (without great trauell) bringeth foorth nothing but thornes and bryers and wéedes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the curſe of God, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to it for mans diſobedience, as ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peareth in Geneſis.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>Et ſpinam et cardu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um proferat tibi.</hi> It ſhall bring foorth thornes and thiſtles vnto thée. Euen ſo, if we behold the fruite of mans nature it bringeth foorth vnto vs nothing but thornes and vnprofitable wéedes, as it is recorded in the Prophet Ezechiell,<note place="margin">Ezech. 2,</note> when he was wylled to goe vnto a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny harted people, and ſuch as had a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots face, and whether they will heare or no, goe thou vnto them, and be not rebellious as they are, for thou ſhalt goe amongſt thornes and Scorpions ſayth the Lord, nowe we muſt conſider that the nature of the thorne is to choke vp euery good ſéede that is ſowne néere him,<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> as appeareth in the Goſpel, where ſome ſéedes fell among thornes, and the thornes grew vp and choked it, ſo when this ground of mans fleſh is ſuch, that
<pb facs="tcp:17676:10"/> can bring foorth nothing but thornes, that is, worldly care, couetouſnes, iuſt or any ſuch vice, it wyll not onely choke vp the good ſeedes of vertue and honeſty that are ſowen in mans eares, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame thornes are rooted vppe to bee caſt into the fire, then ſhall it draw vp by the rootes, ſuch ſéedes as haue hadde but ſmall roote, growing among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thornes, and to the fire they ſhall bothe together. O woefull life, when honeſty and godlines ſhalbe ſowen among ſuch thornes as ſhall choke it vp, and bring it to the fire of eternall damnation, ſuch there be a great many, which haue ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en their godlines among thornes, of whom S. Paule maketh mention, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a taſte of godlines, but denying the vertue thereof, furthermore, we ſée that if a man goe among thornes, as he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelleth, ſometimes this twig catcheth his clothes on this ſide, ſometimes a twig on that ſide, that it doth not onely rent his clothes but his very ſkinne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. Euen ſo when as wee paſſe through the thornes of this world, ſometimes our mindes, ſometime our conſcience is tyed by a twig, but eftſoones our harte
<pb facs="tcp:17676:11"/> is rent and defaced, in ſo much, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding ſome men,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re laketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ogenes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndle at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one day</note> they are ſo defaced, that you ſhall ſcarce know a man from a monſter. Beſides theſe thornes, our corrupt nature, or rather curſed ground is ſuch as doth bring foorth ſo many bad wéedes, (if we looke into nature it ſelfe) that we cannot as much as thinke one good thought, but as the Euangeliſt ſayth, euen from the ſeate of our though<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and affections,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. 15.</note> that is from our hart procéedeth euill thoughts, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, fornications, thefts, murders &amp;c. yea ſuch aboundaunce, and ſo continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that of our ſelues we may well hée called a barren ground,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.4.</note> not able to yéeld any one good fruite, vnleſſe the dewe of heauen, euen the manifold graces, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and goodnes of God be powred vpon vs. And yet (becauſe I will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch to the thirde conſideration) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding,<note place="margin">Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> we finde our ſubſtaunce but fraile earth, and our fruite vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thoughts, we ſéeke dayly to pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the ſame, as though it were made of pure nobility, or of a heauenly and imaculate ſubſtaunce, for we muſt haue it caſed in ſilkes, veluets, &amp; rich robes
<pb facs="tcp:17676:11"/> of dyuers colours and ſtraunge faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we muſt haue it ſtuffed with toſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and delicate choiſes of meates and drinkes, with diuers confections of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deynties, we muſt haue it preſerued in huge houſes, and reſted on eaſy be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, with all as they are appointed to man; ſo are they neceſſary for man, if man would vſe temperancie and not forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, which forgetfulnes maketh him many times, that he neither knoweth his ſubſtaunce whereof it is made, nor his creator wherfore he made it, that in the one he myght bee humble and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, in the other alwaies thankfull, by reaſon whereof we finde our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding darkned, our conſcience hardened, and our harts tranſlated, in ſo much, that if we ſhold reaſon with our ſelues in this our prowde eleuation of minds, what if the poore creatures of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde did ſée and know our boaſting heartes? and had reaſon to diſcerne it, would not the ſilke worme, whoſe web we weare, or the ſhéepe whoſe fléece we put on, or the byrd, on whoſe feathers we eaſilye laye our carcaſes, rather perceiuing a ſuperfluity then a neceſſary vſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:17676:12"/> therewith a monſtrous faſhion rather then a contented mind, would they not laugh more at vs then the byrds did, at the Chough which did put on the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cockes feathers? yes no doubt, and tell vs of our naked comming into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world and of our naked departure,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cleſi. 1.</note> yea and ſay that all is but vaine vanity, better then we our ſelues do expreſſe in our ſelues. Thus much for the firſt name of man, wherein I haue ſet foorth his ſubſtance with the fruites thereof, now to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond man.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Enosh.</head>
               <p>This word <hi>Enosh,</hi> which in Engliſh ſignifieth a man,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſterus.</note> commeth from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall <hi>Anash,</hi> which betokeneth a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone or a thing ſo ouercome with euill, that it is in a manner deſperate or void of any hope of ſafety, euen ſo mankinde after hys fall did firſt ſée his ſubſtaunce, whereof he was made, as I haue ſayde before, then he felt the rewarde of his diſobedience, which is ſignified by thys word <hi>Enosh,</hi> which is as much to ſay, as a miſerable man, mortall, and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly loſt, and although the name was
<pb facs="tcp:17676:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> firſt giuen by <hi>Seth</hi> vnto his ſonne <hi>3727.</hi> yeeres before Chriſt, and after Adam <hi>236.</hi> yeeres, yet ſo was the inuocaſion of <hi>Seth</hi> vnto God; and likewiſe the wyll of God vnto man,<note place="margin">Ally.</note> as to ſignifie vnto <hi>Seth</hi> (being not onely a member, but a head of the generation of the godly) that in the whole members of the Churche ſhould be ſéene among the elect as long as they liued in this world, nothing but miſery, affliction, trouble, calamitye, and perſecution, according to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtle, <hi>As many as wyll liue godlie in Chriſt Ieſu,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</hi> Since which time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly haue very well ſéene, not onely the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience of Adam, but taſted the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaunce and lot of his fall for many mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeries, perſecutions, troubles, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, haue béene ſo heauy and burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the godly,<note place="margin">Phil. 1,</note> that they haue wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed themſelues to bee releaſed of thys life, for to be with God, ſome haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſuch impriſonment, ſuch bondes, ſuch baniſhment, ſuch torments, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be rente wyth wylde beaſtes, ſometimes to be boyled in leade, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times laide on the Grydiron ſome their
<pb facs="tcp:17676:13"/> tongues plucked out, ſome their eyes, ſome let blood to death, and ſome their heads cut of, that it were a moſt lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table matter to lay downe ſuch a blody record. It was no maruell that Saint Paule, Dauid, Stephen, and a great many more godly, deſired to be wyth the Lord,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ita quaſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia taeſa.</note> for that this lyfe ſéemed to bée no more but a weary trauel vnto them. Iob deſcribing the eſtate of man,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ob. 14.1.</note> ſayth, <hi>Man that is borne of a woman is of ſhort continuaunce, &amp; full of trouble,</hi> and trueth it is, that many troubles and chaunges doo happen vnto him, now healthy, ſuddainly ſicke, now rich, and now poore, ſometimes vp, &amp; quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly down, &amp; neuer continuing in a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſtay, ſometimes beloued of one, and ſometimes hated of twenty, nowe merry, and ſuddainly ſorry, now a liue, and to morrow dead, as the wyſe man ſaith, <hi>hodie mihi cras tibi,</hi> to day to mée, to morrow to thée, thys wee ſée the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie of time. Beſides that, if wée looke into the care of our education, the care for the prouiſion of our neceſſaries how to get them, and how to hold them maketh many a man amazed, to ſée the
<pb facs="tcp:17676:13"/> running whéele of Fortune. I myghte ſpeake very much of the ſorrowe and care of men, but it were too long, it ſhal be inough to yéeld the reader to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Map of thys preſent age, wherein we ſée pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to ſlyde away, and children to wexe ſtoute, fréendes to fayle, charitye to growe colde, trueth baniſhed, fayth féeble, againe, iniquity to raigne, enuye and mallice to beare the ſway, &amp; theſe doo ſhewe the eſtate to be ſo ſorrowfull, that a man woulde rather wyſh death with quietnes, then ſuch a life with mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ish,</head>
               <p>An other name that the Hebrewes doo gyue vnto manne is <hi>Ish,</hi> which is found in diuers places of Scripture, but aboue all, I note one place cited out of the ſecond of Geneſis, Therefore let a man forſake Father and Mother,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> &amp;c. which by the Euangeliſts and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell is tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a man, ſome ſuppoſe thys word taketh hys roote fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very eſſentiall power of man,<note place="margin">Iſh.</note> and ſome from hys qualityes, and bothe of them doo accorde with my purpoſe in this ſignification: this is manifeſt, that
<pb facs="tcp:17676:14"/> hée is fleſh, hee is earth, ſo are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beaſtes of the fielde, yet notwithſtanding, God hath made a difference in ſhape, propor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion and honor, as <hi>Ouid</hi> ſayth: <hi>Prona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que cum ſpectent animantia cetera terram Os homini ſublime dedit celumque videre,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Whyle brutiſh beaſtes doo groueling looke,</l>
                     <l>and downeward hang their eyes:</l>
                     <l>Mans countenaunce is lift aloft,</l>
                     <l>and looketh to the skyes.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Yea and though among a great many Philoſophers, their ſubſtaunce ſhall be made equall, yet I finde the greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in man, by howe much he is made the more honourable, not onely in this life, wherein he is made Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of all Gods creatures, &amp; all things are put in ſubiection vnder his féete, but in the world to come,<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> where he ſhall be aſſures of immortalitie and life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, whereas the beaſtes themſelues doo loſe the benefite of honour.</p>
               <p>Before mans fall, in the time of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, there was no ſuch power at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to any creature, as there was vnto man, ſince which time, though
<pb facs="tcp:17676:14"/> man be decayed and fallen into miſerye corruption &amp; depriuation of life in this world, by his diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, yet by Chriſte hee ſhall haue reſtitution to his former beauty and ſtate, ſo that the true defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of <hi>Ish,</hi> in my poore iudgement, is a man in power, decaying himſelfe, and therefore may iuſtly be called <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropos</hi> according to the tranſlation that is to ſay, a ſubuertion or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe, which neuer happened neither by Gods appointment, nor by anye meanes, but by mans owne diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for as man béeing then in power and honour, would wylfully fall and diſhonour himſelfe, as appeareth in the <hi>49</hi> Pſalm.<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.20.</note> Man being in honour hath no vnderſtanding, but is compared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the beaſts that periſh. Euen ſo wée ſée in theſe dayes of reſtitution, wherin Chriſt Ieſus hath appeared perfectly in comfort, in acceptation, in redemption &amp; knowledge, and hath crowned vs with glory, and brought vs into fauour with his father againe, wee not accounting thys fauour nor regarding our reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to honour. Doo wilfully and wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly, fall vnto our olde vomit againe,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:15"/> and in our ſelues doo deface the nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that God hath giuen vs, alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing our ouerthwart diſpoſition, and making it agréeable to our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen nature, which is as much to ſay as a nature turned vp ſide downe, euen as one demaunding once of a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher what a man was, aunſwered, a trée turned vpſide downe, for ſayd hée, as the trée hath his roote downewarde, and groweth vpwarde, hath his nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment below, and ſpreadeth her limmes aboue, euen ſo man hath his roote and nouriſhment in the higher parte, and ſpreadeth hys twigs downewarde, for behold his brayne which féedeth euerye artery downewarde, and beholde euery limme, bone, heayre, arme, legge, &amp;c. and you ſhall finde them all to growe downewarde, not as though nature were an autor or preſident of ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwartnes, but rather that it ſhould bée a remembrance and ſignification of our growing downeward to the earth (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our fleſh) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wee came, and that our roote béeing fedd aboue the earth, did looke vp into heauen, in the which he hath hys perfit féeding, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured
<pb facs="tcp:17676:15"/> life, and although the workes of God are ſo wonderfull in theyr kynde, that we are not able to ſearche out the déepenes of them, nor to reaſon why it ſhould be made thys way or that, yet we may haue an honeſt &amp; godly geſſe in the framing of our ouerthwart na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture when wée ſuruey &amp; iudge our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions agréeable to the ſame, to bee fit fruits for ſuch a trée, and the better to vnderſtand this, doo we not ſée that we account leaſt of that thing which is beſt for vs? and beſt of that which is worſt for vs? doo wee not breake that which is commaunded vs, and followe that which is not commaunded vs, doo we not in ſtéede of godly exerciſes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in fleſhly pleaſures, in ſteede of charity put on enuy? in ſteede of pitty, vſe ſtony harts? doo wee not for pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vſe vengeaunce? for loue hatred, for humility pryde, for liberality couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for vertue vice, for honeſty vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, as the Poet ſayth, <hi>Nitimur in veticum ſemper cupimuſque negata,</hi> we en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deuour our ſelues in things vnlawfull, and alwayes deſire thinges forbidden, we find the like in Adam, who deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:17676:16"/> in the Apple that was forbidden him, and likewiſe in Lots wyfe, that looked backe to Sodome which was for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bidden her, and ſo we ſée and find in all men their vntowardly diſpoſition, wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully to loſe the nobilitie and power of their image and creation, and to caſte theyr honour in the duſt, manne may very well be compared in all his actions vnto the Snayle,<note place="margin">Man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a Snayle.</note> who in his na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture hath theſe thrée properties, hee is ſlowe in going, blinde in ſight, &amp; defileth the way that he goeth in, for commonly you ſhall ſée hys trace. Euen ſo man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, in going any the wayes that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould trauell in, namely the way of godlines, of truth, of fayth, of honeſty, of mercy, of loue, of equity, which are the onely wayes we ſhoulde treade in thys world, we finde him wholly to bée very ſlowe and ſlacke in his pace, and touching his ſight, euen as he hath lame legs to tread his pathes (euen a ſnailes pace) ſo hath hee blinde eyes to ſee the ſame pathes as they ought to bee ſéene, and behold, but rather in hys ſlowe and blind trauell, defileth his paſſage, either with ignoraunce, pride, whoredome, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uye,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:16"/> theft, murther, or ſome one filthye ſinne or other. In ſo much, that if man doo but account the wandring motions of hys mynde, the wylling conſents of his hart, and the wicked actions of hys body, hée ſhall in himſelfe beholde ſuch a filthy account, as if with a conſcience and conſideration, he looke backe and be hold but the trauell of a fewe dayes (I wyll not ſay many yéeres) peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he ſhall be aſhamed to beholde hys defiled pathes, and the ſteppes that hée hath left behind him ſo filthy. O Lorde howe many deſires ariſe in the concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſence of mans fleſh, howe many wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wyſhes ſpring out from the bad af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his hart, howe many vanities haue taken poſſeſſion in his eyes, and howe many felons are written in hys bloddy handes, how many bright daies hée hath occupyed in drouſie ſléepe, to wander in the darke night, howe hée hath obeyed ſathan, &amp; refuſed his ſwéete ſauiour. Howe he hath followed fables, and refuſed the comfortable counſell of the Goſpell, howe he hath turned hys eyes from hys poore afflicted brethren, and followed the wicked crewe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidells,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:17"/> how he hath ſhut vp his compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the poore, and opened his libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality to drunkards, wantons, and light perſons, what greater loſſe of nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie cane there be, then to refuſe the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious company of heauen, yea euen that ſwéete Chriſt himſelfe, and to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant with ſathan &amp; hys crew, what greater deformity, then to flee from the protection of the almighty, to be ſubiecto eyther to the fleſh or to the world, and what greater ſhame, then to caſt of the iewels of honeſty and godlines, and to be bankerupt with the infidels of thys worlde, not able to boaſt of one good work, no not ſo much as delighted with one godly thought. God himſelfe hath proclaimed all his ſeruice to be doone in the open light, and open places, and in all congregations, namely faith, loue, charity, pitty, patience, equity, the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of hys word, the vſing of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, inſomuch, that he that is hys ſeruaunt, in theſe thinges may boldly knocke his breaſt and ſay, <hi>Hic mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus aheneus eſto nil conſcere ſibi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Horace E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſto. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>nulla im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palleſcere culpa.</hi> To know no guiltines, and to bluſh at no offence, is a braſen
<pb facs="tcp:17676:17"/> wall, on the otherſide, ſathan ſhutteth vp all hys workes in hugger munger, he wyll haue none of the come in light, as for example, the théefe, the whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger, the drunkard, and euery euill dooer wyl not be knowne of his action, neyther committe any of theſe wycked offences in the ſight of the worlde, but ſecretelie and in feare of daunger, yet notwithſtanding, ſuch is the folly of thys world, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peruerſnes of mans nature, that notwithſtanding that light be come into the worlde,<note place="margin">Iohn 3.19</note> yet men loue darknes more then light, becauſe theyr déedes are euill. Thus you ſée the whole ſtate of man deſcribed, and his lyfe to conſiſt of a weake ſubſtaunce, his eſtate in myſery, and his honour caſt downe to the grounde.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:18"/>
            <head>A prayer.</head>
            <p>O Eternall God and moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full father, who of thine owne goodnes haſte vouchſafed to frame vs of a vile ſubſtance &amp; made vs to thine owne ſimilitude, and likenes, and didſt ſet our firſt parents Adam and Eue in the pleaſant Paradiſe and didſt crown them with innocency &amp; immortality which they loſt by their diſobedience, plucking vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; their poſterity thy iuſt curſe, by the which wee alwayes in this tranſitorye world, ſauour of ſin, ſorrowe &amp; death, yet thou of thy goodnes O Lord, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting thy wrath, and remembring thy mercy, didſt giue vs thy ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to reſtore vs againe to our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and bring vs againe into thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, who hath already entred the gates, &amp; taken poſseſsion for vs in thy heauenly Paradiſe, where wee ſhall bee
<pb facs="tcp:17676:18"/> aſsured of euerlaſting comfort, ioy and bleſsednes. Vouchſafe (O Lorde) wee humbly beſeech thee, to comfort our harts with thy holy ſpirite, and open our vnderſtandings with the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all preaching of thy holy worde, that we may truely acknowledge thee to be our onely creator, preſeruer and redee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer, and that we may ſo viewe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold our owne lamentable eſtate, and hauing our owne inſufficiencie alwaies b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore our eyes, may alwayes flee to thee for ſuccour, graunt O Lord that wee may ſo acknowledge our owne weakenes, that we bee not caryed away with vaine pompe, nor fed with filthy pleaſure and luſt, nor drawen away by the allurements of the world, but may alwaies ſettle a firme confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in thee, which art the only ſtay &amp; gage of our frayle and caſuall eſtate, for thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, our onely media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and aduocate. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="explanation">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:19"/>
            <head>¶ Howe Sinne doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes budde forth and grow in our nature, and how it is nouriſhed and encreaſed in our fleſh.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. 2.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ithence the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine defect, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of nature in man, by the which hée is prone and ready to commit ſin, and neuer able fully to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie the Lawe of God, this corruptnes lieth hidden and taketh roote in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ours, which procéeded from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and buddeth or breaketh foorth by the thoughts and wyll of the hart, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enclined vnto euill, euen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole courſe of our life,<note place="margin">en. 8.21.</note> as God himſelfe ſayd, <hi>The imagination of mans hart is euill, euen from hys youth.</hi> Although we ſée
<pb facs="tcp:17676:19"/> in youth no ſuch apparant ſhowe of ſin, as wée doo in ryper yéeres, yet that euil which is called originall or inhabiting, dooth aſſuredly ſo remaine, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time is ſéene anger, reuenge &amp; vntruth in them, and then concupiſcence, which ſticketh in nature from the beginning, and aptnes to ſin dooth appeare euerye day more and more, euen as age dooth encreaſe, and then as S. Iames fayth,<note place="margin">Ia. 1.14.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> He is drawen away by his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, and is enticed, then when luſt hath conceiued, it bringeth foorth ſinne, and ſinne when it is finiſhed bringeth foorth death. Sinne it ſelfe is found in our corrupt nature, but the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and encreaſing thereof, is ſéene in the maturitye and ripenes of yéeres. Touching the firſt ſinne and ſimple ſin, which is called Originall. The prophet ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note> 
               <hi>Behold I was ſhapen in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, and in ſinne hath my mother conceaued me.</hi> Likewiſe S. Paul doth ſay, <hi>By nature we are the Children of wrath.</hi> Hence we gather in the verye generation of man, when by the Lawe of nature the iſſue is conceaued and fra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, then the ſpotte of ſinne dooth paſſe
<pb facs="tcp:17676:20"/> into them begotten, and ſo from age to age, and from one to another paſſeth ſin euen with the framing and conception of nature, and then (as the Prophet ſayth) in an ther place, <hi>who can make that clean which is conceaued of an vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleane ſeede.</hi> If that ſéede then be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, néedes muſt the fruites be agrée able which doo appeare in order as in a ſéede, firſt there is the very graine, from thence the ſtalke, laſt, the very ſame fruite: ſo in man, firſt the dokled na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by diſcent euen from Adam, then his thoughts, laſtly his actions &amp; déedes. Now touching the firſt, we receiue our contamination in generation, from the defiled generator, then our thoughtes begin to frame a conſent and ſhape of ſinne, and it is working in our hartes and mindes when it is ſayd, we cannot as much as thinke one good thought, as appeareth in the Goſpell.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th. 15.19.</note> 
               <hi>Out of the hart come euill thoughs, murders, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, fornications, thefts, falſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies, ſlaunders.</hi> So that firſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harte is the ſéede, then from thence procéedeth the thought or imagination, which in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>8.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 8.</note> of Gen. is called <hi>Gezer,</hi> a cogitation or
<pb facs="tcp:17676:20"/> cuſpicence, which doth ſhape a delight, a pleaſure, a wyll and deſire to ſinne, and laſt of all appeareth in the ſame work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of nature, the very fruites of our corruptnes which ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is called <hi>Atoxia,</hi> which is a confuſion of order, not framing our ſelues according to the Law of God, foraſmuch as in our ſelues, we behold not that which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for our ſelues, or required in our ſelues, as the Apoſtle ſaith: The natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man beholdeth not thoſe thynges that are of the ſpirite of God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.1.</note> &amp; for thys cauſe are we called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> wicked, and lewde, for when we haue doone of our ſelues what we can, yet we are vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable in reſpecte of our owne abilitye and power, which I ſpeake not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weaker ſort, to ſignifie vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their valure before God and the world, to be nothing worth, and ſo to bee reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and not regarded, but rather to their great comfort, that being ſo vile and wicked in their kinde and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it pleaſeth almighty God to beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifye them wyth the ſpyrite of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: and allowe of them in hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable acceptation, and to bleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:17676:21"/> them with his continuall mercye and loue in his ſonne Ieſus CHRIST, eſpecially thoſe that féele the heauye burden of the fleſh and wyll hearken to the louing call of the Lord, and come vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to him, but ſuch as wyll not hearken and returne when they are called, but perſeuer and continue in the hardnes of their hart, in ſuch this hroode of ſinne is nouriſhed and encreaſed two manner of wayes.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wo wayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed.</note> 
               <hi>1.</hi> By the dilligence of ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſecondly by the pleaſure of the fleſh. As touching the dilligence of ſathan, when ye ſhall perceiue manne to goe aſtraye from God, which is his preſeruer and ſhéepeheard, and from the comfortable flocke of the Church, and company of the godly, then as a ſtraying ſhéepe is, he the ſooner taken by the Woolfe, and ſo deuoured of him, for ſathan diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goeth about as a roaring Lyon, ſéeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom he may deuoure, and when he hath taken him, euen as the fleſhe of the ſhéepe is digeſted in the ſtomacke of the Woolfe, euen ſo is this wicked ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſolued into the inticements &amp; ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of ſathan, ſo that where as the motions of the fleſh doo prick and ſtirre,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:21"/> there is ſathan ready to ſette forwarde and egge man vnto the accompliſhing of euery ſinnefull deſire, vntill it be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formed, and then followeth the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; conſumption of the whole man, eyther in ſhame or confuſion, thys hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth chéefeſt in thoſe that goe firſte aſtray and forſake theyr louing GOD,<note place="margin">Strayers.</note> to whom he hath louingly called and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelfe, and then afterward ſhal followe the wandring of their owne wyll, as appeared in Iudas, who fyrſte forſooke hys God, followed hys owne wyll, and then was taken of ſathan, and ſo conſumed. And now to conclude in thys poynt, there is no roote or ſéede of ſinne in the hart of man, but ſathan is alwayes watring it, and attending it, to make it growe and waxe rype, and being ſo, it is reapt either with ſhame, or rewarded with confuſion, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſayth, What profite had yee in thoſe thinges whereof yée are nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed. Dauid to auoyd it, ſayd in hys prayer to God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.2.</note> 
               <hi>All they that hope in thee shall not be ashamed.</hi> ſo likewiſe after the continuaunce of ſin commeth confuſion, as we haue ſéene by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:22"/> many whoremongers, haue béene brought to extreame pouerty or to moſt horrible diſeaſes, the drunkard vnto the dropſie, and extreame pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes and ſéeble<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, the tyrant vnto vtter ruine hatr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and corruption,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 7.</note> as appeared by <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> who did ſo rotte where hee laye, that his Chamberlayne could not abide the ſmell of him. The couetous, God doth abhorre, as the Prophet ſayth, the Rebel is rewarded, (as woorthely) with the loſſe of his life, beſides their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall puniſhments layd vpon ſome of the vngodly. The Apoſtle ſayth vnto all the vngodly, <hi>Neyther fornicators, nor Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Co. 6.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>nor wantons, nor adulterers, nor theeues, nor couetous, nor drunkerdes, nor raylers, nor extortioners, ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite the kingdome of God,</hi> this ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be gréeuous and terrible ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and all theſe ſinnes are ſtyrring in our fleſh, but vrged and ſette on by ſathan, who ſéeketh (as I ſayd) nothing but ſhame and confuſion. Now there re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteth an other ſort of nouriſhing of this ſin in our fleſhly nature, when we giue ouer our ſelues as ſeruants to vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and iniquity,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om 6.19</note> to commit iniquity, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:17676:22"/> bée ouercome either with pleaſure or with idlenes, or with aboundaunce, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe take hold in our fleſhly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and we anker our wylles therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, then that ſin which ſtirreth in hidden nature, appeareth in open actions, as for example, the man that is giuen to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whether it be the pleaſure of the minde, or of the fleſh, as Herode was giuen to both, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effect of them was mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther againſt his owne conſcience, and if you giue ſcope vnto the wandring mind to haue his delights wherein he wil, as we ſée many delights in the world, as hawking, hunting, dycing, carding, py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, dauncing, bare-bayting, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſuch paſtimes, ſometimes they are taken for recreations, but that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the graue, that knoweth howe to rule (not to be ruled) but giue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carnal minde an inche, and it deſireth an Ell, and hardly it can be remooued or appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed becauſe it is in league &amp; lincked to the fleſh, which alwaies deſireth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſpirite, and that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe we ſée greater flocking, &amp; more delight in any theſe pleaſures among the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter company, then in reſorting to Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:23"/> or to the Churche, hence gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the greate abuſe of the Sabaoth day, in bowſing, drinking, gaming and paſtime. The heathen Poet did gyue good counſell, <hi>Animum rege, qui niſi paret imparat hunc frenis hunc tu compeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce cataena.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Rule thy minde, vnles thy minde rule thée, bridle him, and fetter him faſt with chaynes. For this cauſe did the Apoſtle gyue counſell, that wée ſhould mortify our earthly members, that is to ſay, Kyll our carnall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and delights. But doo we goe about to kyll them when wee water them? and allowe of them? nay rather prefer them before godly meditations. I wyll not condemne pleaſures (as I ſay) that are vſed of the wiſe and well ſetled for their recreations, nor yet our Engliſhe muſicke, vnles it be among wanton mindes or light braynes, for if it be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed among them,<note place="margin">Effect of Muſicke.</note> you ſhall ſée what a monſtrous effecte it vſeth, it maketh theyr thoughts and mindes to runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray a great waye of, and fall into dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſundry deſires and vnlawfull wiſhes, and ambitious appetites, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, it ſhapeth a thouſande fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and imaginations in theyr conceits
<pb facs="tcp:17676:23"/> making themſelues in their fantaſies to be of great valure, and eſtimation, whereas they are nothing towarde, to what proportion eyther of behauiour, ambition, or deſire they frame them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that be louers of Muſicke, they can beſt iudge that haue delighted it, but this I am ſure, though preferred in many houſes before the preaching of the Goſpell, yet I knowe the Goſpell delighteth the godly ſo much, as they vtterly refuſe muſicke, in reſpect of the greater, for in the Goſpell we finde this ſwéete harmony,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> the gates of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are open, mercy and loue is ſent vnto vs, euerlaſting life is prepared for vs, in the kingdome of heauen, and what bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter melody. The other yéeldeth but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine ſoundes, not diſtinct, lightlye heard and quickly gon, and therefore fitter rather for an vnſenſible fleſh then for a reaſonable ſpirite, and thys plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the minde beeing firſt growen ſtrong and ripe in the minde, dooth worke in the fleſh ſo mightily, that all good order being excluded, theſe are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Firſt idlenes, then the delight of euill company, thirdly euill and filthy
<pb facs="tcp:17676:24"/> words, and laſt, immoderate dyet, and what procéedeth from all theſe <hi>4.</hi> you ſhall iudge by the ſequell. As for the firſt, which is Idlenes, the Poete ſayth, <hi>Otia ſi tollas periere Cupidinis ercus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idlenes.</note> Take away Idlenes, and thou dooſt breake Cupides bowe, againe.</p>
            <q>Queritur Aegistus quare ſit factus adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? In promptu cauſa est, deſidioſus erat.</q>
            <p>Why was <hi>Aegiſtus</hi> an adulterer? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was Idle. King Dauid came from hys fluggiſh bed at noone day, and walked on the roofe of hys houſe, when he beheld from thence, <hi>Bath-ſheba</hi> the wyfe of <hi>Vriah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2, Sam, 11.2.</note> and did by hys idlenes engender hys adulterous practize. The wiſe man ſaith, Idlenes bringeth much euill.<note place="margin">Eccl. 33, 26</note> Likewiſe S. Paul ſpeaketh of young wyddowes to Timothy: Being idle they learn to goe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> houſe to houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1, Tim. 5, 13.</note>Now to the next vice, which is euill company, which is a great occaſion to tranſlate a good diſpoſition, and make it become very bad,<note place="margin">Euill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye.</note> as the wyſe man ſaith <hi>Ex malo conſortio malus eris,</hi> by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the wicked, thou ſhalt learne wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.2.</note> The children of God being in the company of the daughters of wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:17676:24"/> men, diſcending of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtocke of <hi>Cain,</hi> were rauiſhed with their beautye, and tooke them agaynſt the wyll of God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as he beholding the wickednes of their harts, ſayd: <hi>It repenteth me that I made man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 13.1.</note> It is ſayd in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticus, He that toucheth Pitch ſhal be defiled with it. Alſo in the Reuelation it is ſayd, by the whore of Babilon: Goe put of her my people that ye be not par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>takers in her ſinnes.<note place="margin">Reu. 18.4</note> If a Lambe ſtand by a Woolfe, or towe néere the fire, the one ſhalbe in hazard to be deuoured, the other to be burned. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goe among bryers, he ſhalbe plucked, ſcratched and defaced in euery ſide, euill company hath wholy conſumed many a man, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credited his houſe, blotted out his good name, impoueriſhed his eſtate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the body in moſt horrible diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. The Prodigall childe, that fell into bad company, is a good example to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny prodigall children in Englande, to make them auoyd that thing that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſhame, diſeaſes, pouerty, hanging, or ſome other bad death, there is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo vnreaſonable, but he will auoyde the plague, leproſie and ſuch contagious
<pb facs="tcp:17676:25"/> diſeaſes, and ſhun and deteſt ſuch as are infected with them, but thoſe ſpirituall diſeaſes, as doo infect both body &amp; ſoule, are neuer auoyded nor deteſted, nor the company of them that haue them: the horrible puniſhment whereof, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in many places of Scripture, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if you reade y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Homily againſte adultery, there is a moſt terrible pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ordeyned of God in all ages, againſt adulterous perſonnes, of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and degrées, yet we haue a great many ſtony harts, hauing vyſardes of impudency on their faces, that do know God, haue heard his word &amp; his threats againſt ſuch horrible ſinne, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding wyll delight in that filthy and damnable ſinne, and wyll buylde (preſumptuouſly) on the mercy of God, but this let them be warned, and in the bowels of Chriſt I charge them take héede, that they build not theyr pleaſure and luſt, but theyr fayth vpon the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, if they doo, the building wyll fall euen as Sampſons houſe did vpon theyr owne pates, and cruſh them to péeces, for the ſeruaunt that knoweth hys Maſters wyll, and wyll not doo it,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:25"/> ſhall be whypped with many ſcourges, If ſuch adulterers wyll not bee terrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the temporall puniſhments of which before are layd downe, yet lette them looke to the day of iudgement, where the vpright Iudge Chriſt ſitteth who hath pronounced the ſwéete ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence already in Mathew.<note place="margin">Math. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Verily I ſay vnto you, that when the ſonne of man ſhall ſit in the throne of hys maieſtye, ye which followed me in the regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall ſyt alſo vpon the xii. thrones and iudge the twelue tribes of Iſraell. And whoſoeuer ſhall forſake houſe or brethren, or ſiſters, or father or mother or wyfe or children or landes for my names ſake, he ſhall receiue an hundred fold more, and ſhall inherite euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.</hi> Let them looke into thys ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and they ſhall find a promiſed pleaſure, which ſhall drowne all carnall and filthy delights, if at leaſt wiſe hée haue any deſire to be the child of God, and doo expect and looke for the lyfe to come.</p>
            <p>The thyrd vice, which corrupteth a man is filthy talke,<note place="margin">3. Vice fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy talke</note> which indéede dooth ſet our nature ſo at liberty, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhame
<pb facs="tcp:17676:26"/> not to fall in the ſandes and ſhore of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy pleaſure, for if the tongue, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſayth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 3.4.</note> be the helme and guyde of the ſhyp of our body, néedes muſt the ſhip run at large, whoſe guyde is vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor, 15.</note>S. Paule recording the wordes of <hi>Menander,</hi> ſayd: Euill words corrupt good manners. Likewiſe Dauid deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the vngodly, among other things ſayth: Vnder his tongue is vngodlines and vanitie.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 3.6</note> Yea Iames ſayth, The tongue ſet among our members, defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the whole body, and ſetteth on fire the courſe of nature, and eſpecially you ſhall note it in thoſe whoſe inclination is to euill, and in whom there is founde a towardnes, and a wylling readines to a wanton, wicked, and filthy life, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I fréendly admoniſh with S. Paul Fornication,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph. 5.34.5.</note> and all vncleannes, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes, let it not be once named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, as it becommeth Saintes, Neyther filthynes nor fooliſh talking, neyther ieſting, which are thinges not comelye, but rather gyuing of thankes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:26"/>
            <p>Laſt of all, there remaineth an other ſuſtenaunce to carnall pleaſure which is immoderate diet,<note place="margin">Immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate dyet,</note> an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to all temperancy, an ouerthrowe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fer out of reaſon, a diſfigurer of ſhape, and a murtherer of vertue. Likewiſe, a fréede vnto vice, a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of appetite, and a copartner with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>lines, for if you behold the man in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ned eyther to gluttony or drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, you beholde him that dooth ſo ſtuffe the fleſh, as he ſéemeth to be wylling to féede the effectes and deſires thereof, whych appeared ſhamefully bothe in Lot and in Holophernus, to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. And as <hi>Marcinus</hi> ſayth, <hi>Tu ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea indulges Ciprian ſectare nefandam,</hi> So thou dooſt fauour gluttony, that in the ende, thou dooſt nouriſh venerye. The wiſe man ſayth,<note place="margin">Ecc. 31.30</note> Drunkennes en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſeth the courage of a foole, till he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende, it dimiſheth his ſtrength, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth wounds? Alſo in the Prouerbes of Salomon.<note place="margin">Pro. 23, 31, 32, 33.</note> Looke not thou vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyne when it is red, and when it ſheweth hys colour in the cuppe, or goeth downe pleaſantlie, in the end therof it wil bite like a ſerpent, &amp; hurt like a Cockatrice,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:27"/> thine eyes ſhall looke vpon ſtrange wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and thy hart ſhall ſpeake lewde thinges. Héerein you may ſée the lewde forces of exceſſiue wine, it maintaineth venery, gyueth courage to offende, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſheth ſtrength, woundeth, ſtingeth as a ſerpent, hurteth like a Cockatrice, turneth the eyes to ſtraunge women, and maketh the hart ſpeake lewde thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, what greater ouerthrow can there be to the honour and dignity of a man. Now beholde what God pronounceth againſt ſuch. In the Prophet Eſay hée ſayth?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 5, 11</note> Woe vnto them that riſe vppe earely to folow drunkennes, &amp; to them that continue vntill night, till the wine doo enflame them. And a little after, in the ſame Chapter.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſe, 22,</note> Woe vnto them that are mighty to drinke wine, and to them that are ſtrong to powre in ſtrong drinke.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el, 1, 5,</note> Likewiſe, the Prophet Ioel cryeth out at them. Awake ye drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kardes, and wéepe and howle, all yée drinkers of wyne, becauſe of the newe wyne, for it ſhalbe pulled from your mouth. Nowe becauſe mans nature is apt and prone héerevnto, God did not onely gyue a threatning to this reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:17676:27"/> to be terrified but an order to his bodye to be mortified, and therefore ordeyned and proclaimed faſting,<note place="margin">Faſting.</note> as a moſt godly and commendable conſtitution of the body in temperancye, and that wee ſhold ſo order our dyet, that we ſhoulde be féeders of nature, and not releuers of appetite, neyther ſhould this faſting ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticiouſly conſiſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> choyſe of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and drinkes, as the Maniches did,<note place="margin">Auguſt. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moribus. Manich, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2, cap, 13,</note> which refrayned fleſh, and yet in other dainties were <hi>distenti &amp; crepantes,</hi> but rather that we ſhoulde take to relieue nature, and no more. To this ende ſayth Caluin, was faſting ordeyned,<note place="margin">Inſtitu, li, cap, 12. ſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 15,</note> firſt to ſupproſſe the fleſh, leaſt that it ſhoulde were wanton. Secondly they ſhould be the better gyuen to prayer, and thirdly it ſhould be a teſtimony vnto humility, in thoſe that did vſe faſting orderly, that is to ſaye, in refraining ouermuch ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing and pampering of the bellye, the Lord God graunt it ſpéedily in all good Chriſtians for his Chriſts ſake. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:28"/>
            <head>A prayer.</head>
            <p>O Mercifull God, foraſmuch as wee ſee that we are but very duſt and ashes, and though wee growe vp glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly as the flower of the fielde, yet we are cut downe quickly and wyther as the graſſe, and foraſmuch as out of this corruptible nature of ours, proceedeth no good thing, but wicked thoughtes, deuilish inuentions and moſte damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble actions. VVe humbly beſeech thee, gyue vs grace that wee may ſo beholde our vile nature and wicked inclination that we may be ashamed at the fruites thereof, that by shame we may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to shun the wickednes of ſin, and forced to shadow our ſelues vnder the winges of thy protection, and learne to put on the beautye of thy ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that in him wee may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the shape and forme of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and godlines, to the honour and glory of thy holy name, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="explanation">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:28"/>
            <head>Howe many greeuous enemies we haue by reaſon of ſinne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering howe ouglye and monſtrous ſinne is in the mind &amp; fleſhe of man,<note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note> and howe diuerſe it is in hys wyll, as it is a thinge impoſſible to proportionate it, ſo is it a thing ſo deteſtable, that by reaſon ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, (I meane ſinne onely) we haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moſt gréeuous and intollerable ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. As for example, Gods vengance and wrath, our owne conſcience, death and damnation, of the which, ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are enemies vnto our ſin &amp; fréends vnto vs, as are, Gods vengeaunce, and our owne conſcience: and ſome of them are fréends vnto ſinne, and enemies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, as are, death and damnation, but by reaſon that ſinne raigneth in vs, and we fauour it, and water it, and cannot nor wyll not ſeperate our ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hazarde of it, but kéepe a ſociety wyth it. Wée are like the Corne that is
<pb facs="tcp:17676:29"/> is found among the chaffe, which is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered vp &amp; caſt into the fire, and ſo they periſh togeather: Euen ſo, when ſinne is founde to excéede in our mortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and that we ouermuch defile the houſe of the Lorde, (I meane his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) he ſhal come with his Fanne in his hand, and purge hys flower, and that ſéede which is not ſéene, but couered with the Chaffe, and duſt of the flowre, ſhall be caſt away, and that man whoſe multitude of ſinnes doo couer him ſo, that neyther repentaunce, nor any good conuerſation doth diſcouer, vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eyther the broome of Gods vengance ſhall ſwéepe him away, or els y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worme of his conſcience ſhall gnaw him, or the ſting of death ſhall confound him, or els the fire of hell ſhall conſume him, for all theſe are enimies vnto vs for ſins ſake. Nowe therefore, leaſt ſinne myght raigne among vs too aboundantly, with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out the cutting off of the buddings and bloſſomes of it, either with amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with grace or with feare, I wyll laye downe what the force of all thoſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies is, that we may ſée how that day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the entertainement of ſinne, wée
<pb facs="tcp:17676:29"/> prouoke gréeuous enimies againſt vs. And touching the firſt, which is the ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geaunce of God vpon ſinners.<note place="margin">Vengeance of God.</note> I wyll begin with the Hyſtory of the Iſralites expreſſed in the Bookes of Exodus and Numery, where the people for theyr murmuring, wyſhing of their fleſhpots for worſhipping the Golden Calfe,<note place="margin">Exo, 15, 16, 17, 19, 32, Chapters.</note> and many other ſinnes, had the plague, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie and gréeuous diſeaſes among them, and many of the Idolaters were ſlayne. And in Numery, ſuch as rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led were ſwallowed vppe in the earth,<note place="margin">Chapters, 16, 21, 25,</note> ſuch as murmured, had firye Serpents ſent among them, and ſuch as commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted fornication among them, hadde the plague, in ſo much, as there dyed in the plague twentye foure thouſande. We reade alſo that for the ſinnes of the people, the world was drowned, and for the ſinne of Sodome and Gomor,<note place="margin">Gen, 6, 13,</note> thoſe Citties were conſumed with fire and brimſtone. Horoſius reporteth,<note place="margin">Gen, 19, 24,</note> that for ſinne the two great Citties in Aſia, Coloſſa and Hierapolis, ſuncke into the earth, and were ſwallowed vp. Iericho was beſiged by Ioſua, and the Cittye was taken,<note place="margin">Ioſu, 6, 21,</note> and all the inhabitants (ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:17676:30"/> Rahab, and they that were wyth her) bothe olde and young were put to the ſworde, and the Citty burnt, but of all lamentable plagues ſent from God, the deſtruction of Ieruſalem by <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpaſian,</hi> may be a terrible exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto vs, for they hadde the Lawe, Prophets,<note place="margin">Math, 11.</note> yea Chriſt himſelfe, who bitterly wept ouer them, and yet they would not turne from theyr wicked ſinne, but hardned theyr harts, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not for the Lords ſwéete warning, and comfortable calling, nor yet for their owne harme and confuſion, which was ſo néere at hande, but euer they thought that the Lorde woulde not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory hys Temple among them, nor yet that they ſhoulde bee ſpoyled for their Temples ſake, and beſides that they were ſo many, they boaſted of their mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude and ſtrength, and thought all the worlde could not ouercome, but all the world cannot preuayle, where God him ſelfe doſt ſette againſt, as appeared by this great and populous Ieruſalem. Whereof Ioſephus maketh mention, that they were beſieged ſo long, that a buſhell of Corne, was worth a talent,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:30"/> yea they were ſo hungry, that they dyd eate the Leather of their Targets and ſhooes,<note place="margin">Anno ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. 73.</note> and glad were ſome of them to eate the dunge of Oxen, the mother kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her owne child to eate if, which was a moſt lamentable &amp; vnnaturall thing, there were x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.C.M. beſides Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>leans ſlayne by Veſpaſian, xvii.M. ſent to Alexandria by Titus, to be kept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vile bondage. Two thouſand to be brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Rome for a triumph, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward were deuoured of wylde beaſtes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es that, xxv.M. Iewes were ſold, all this gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> multitude, (which man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thought could haue conque<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their ſinnes, and for the contemning of hys word and trueth, deliuered vppe to the bloddy hands of their enimies. What har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſo hard that wyll not tremble to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e this lamentable vengeaunce and wrath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, with ſo ſharpe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon his owne people, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he loued ſo well, and among all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations of the worlde, choſe for his peculiar flocke.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hayle, thunder, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſtormes, tempeſt, fluds, miſts, pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
<pb facs="tcp:17676:31"/> darknes, frogges, caterpillers, and firye ſerpents, which the Lorde hath ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hys people for ſin. The Prophet ſaith that for the ſinnes of the people, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord wil ſend a dearth vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not of bread and oyle onely, but of hys holye worde, and therfore for their Idolatry and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity,<note place="margin">Eze. 14,</note> the Lorde ſent falſe Prophets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and the Lord ſent word vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the people by the Prophet Ezechiell. That if they did ſinne by committing any treſpaſſe againſt him, he woulde ſtretch foorth hys hande and break the ſtaffe of bread, and ſende ſuch a famine vpon it, that man and beaſte ſhoulde bée deſtroyed, likewiſe be would ſende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e beaſtes into the lande to ſpoyle it, a ſword to deſtroy them, or a peſtilence to ouerthrowe man and beaſt, and their if Noab, Daniell, and Iob were among them, they ſhold deliuer but theyr owne ſoules, but their ſonnes and daughters ſhould not be deliuered. How bitterly were the offences of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hab and Iezabel puniſhed for the taking away of a little péece of land. I would to God it were ſéene in England, by them that taketh away great liuings and manours, and
<pb facs="tcp:17676:31"/> ſendeth a whole houſholde it begging, if the ſonnes of thoſe menne were ſo vſed as Achabs ſonnes, theyr heads cut of all in one day, and likewyſe theyr hungrye Iezabels, were vſed as Achabs. Iezabel deuoured of dogs, and foules of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aire, they would (I thinke) conſider what a a God there is, that ſéeeth into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harts of wicked offenders, and dooth beholde the multitude of their ſinnes, not onely entertained in corrupt nature, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in corrupt wyll. Good Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the ripenes of ſinns in theſe dayes, it is to be lamented, that wee feare not the vengeaunce of God.<note place="margin">Eze, 16, 19</note> The Prophet Dauid could ſay, <hi>If thy wrath be kindled O Lord, who may abide it.</hi> Ezechiell doth ſhewe howe greatly the Lorde cryed out againſt Ieruſalem, ſhewing the offences of Sodome, for the which they were deſtroyed, whych were, pryde, fulnes of bread, Idlenes and contemning the poore. But alas we haue not onely thys, but an infinite more of moſt horrible ſins raigning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. As diſobedience, murther, enuy, couetouſnes, horedome, extortion, vſury, falſe accuſation, drunkennes,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:32"/> lying, diſſimulation and periury, from the iuſt iudgement of which ſins nowe ripe among vs, I beſéeche God of hys mercy defend vs, and be fauourable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. Truely our owne ſins of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d béeing ſo many, and ſo boldly and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vſed, doo blind vale a great many that they neither beholde the maieſtye and authority of God, not yet the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice he may lay vpon vs, as barrennes, dearth, famine, and peſtilence, and in ſtéede of our great plenty, to ſende vs ſcarcity, in ſtéede of our peace to ſend vs warre, and for the quietnes of our ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations and families, to baniſh vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our owne houſes, and to ſcatter our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies before our faces, and to deliuer them and vs into our aduerſaries hand as a pray. This God can doo, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les we ſpéedily repent, vndoubtedly this firſt enemy to ſin, which is Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce, wyll be powred vpon vs.</p>
            <p>The ſecond enemy vnto ſinne, is our owne conſcience,<note place="margin">Second ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to ſin.</note> which foraſmuch as it hath an inward taſte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature &amp; a knowledge of our deformed conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation &amp; a ſight of our going a ſtray from the image of our good creator, doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb facs="tcp:17676:32"/> at the rebellion of ſin (eſpecially when we ioyne our wils therto) ſtir in our bodies as though we had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> féeling of ſome liuing thing there, crawling,<note place="margin">Syntereſis</note> gnawing, clogging, accuſing, preſſing down as a heauy lump of lead, ſhaming at, &amp; condemning our own reaſons, and wils for giuing entertainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto ſin, in aſmuch as ſometimes ye ſhal find the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; gréeues of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to worke greater ſorrow &amp; care in our minds, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if we were either in priſon or ready to goe to execution, and although there bée <hi>2.</hi> conſciences, the good and the bad,<note place="margin">Two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as I write vnto the good people of God, I will haue to doo but with the conſcience of the good, referring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other to his continual hardnes. And although oftentimes we ſée not the conſcience of the good, by their wickednes of ſin, for that they are not yet called, yet if theyr conſciences do not ſhew her force of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, no doubt it is impriſoned, and ſo hid in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great heape of corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that though it cannot now ſpeake in the end wil breake foorth, &amp; that we ſée in many diſordered perſonnes in theſe daies which in the hardneſſe of their hartes
<pb facs="tcp:17676:33"/> haue contynued in theyr ſinne a long tyme, vntouched or vndiſcloſed. Yet in the ende, when God wyll call them, or ſathan bring them to ſhame, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no man can iuſtly accuſe them, (how be it ſuſpect them of euill liuing) being cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led to examinacion before any magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, then who can better accuſe then the conſcience, (who doth firſt condemn and then ſtrike a great feare) in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende produceth two witneſſes, that is eyther the ſtammering tongue, or els the bluſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing face to accuſe the guilty wyth hys owne mouth, and make him ſpeake al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſée eyther ſhame to diſcredite him, or the magiſtrate to puniſh hym or the Gallowes to confound him. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the conſcience called <hi>Mille teſtes,</hi> a thouſand witneſſes, becauſe it dooth more euidently know that which is hid in him, then a thouſand men, and dooth boyle and burne in the harts of wicked men like a fire. As Tully ſayth, <hi>Nolite putare (quemadmodum in fabulis ſepenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero videtis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In oratione pro Roſcio</note> 
               <hi>eos qui aliquid impie, ſcelera te que commiſerunt agitari &amp; perterreri taedis ardentibus ſua quemque fraus ſuus terror maxime vexat, ſuum quemque ſce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lus
<pb facs="tcp:17676:33"/> exagitat, amentiaque afficit, ſuae malae cogitationes, conſcientiaeque animi terrent &amp;c.</hi> Thinke not as Poets haue fayned, that they that haue committed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vngodly or wickedly, are vexed and ſcourged with burning Torches, it is our owne guile, and our owne feare doth moſt trouble vs, it is our owne wickednes doth torment vs and amaze vs, our owne wicked thoughts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences that dooth affright vs &amp;c. There is a great accuſation of the conſcience in the hart of the ſinner, as when the Scribes and Phariſies had taken a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in adultery, they brought her to Chriſt to ſée what ſentence he woulde gyue againſt her, becauſe they hadde found in Moſes Lawe, that ſuch a one ſhould be ſtoned to death, but they dyd it not for Iuſtice, but to tempt him. Then he writ wyth hys finger on the ground, and ſaid: (béeing vrged by them for his ſentence) <hi>Let him that is among you without ſinne caſt the firſt ſtone at her. And when they heard it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.7.9</note> 
               <hi>being accuſed by their owne conſciences, they went out one by one, beginning at the eldeſt euen vnto the laſt,</hi> It is
<pb facs="tcp:17676:34"/> moſt true that <hi>Iuuenall</hi> ſayth:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t, 13,</note>Euaſiſse putes quos diri conſcia facti</l>
                  <l>Mens reddit attonitos, et ſurdo verbere caedit.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Dooſt thou thinke he can eſcape, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conſcience of a moſte horrible facte maketh amazed, and whippeth with a deafe ſcourge. And as the ſame <hi>Iuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> ſaith in an other place. <hi>Nocte di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eque ſuum gestat in pectore testem.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>But day and night, where that he goe or reſt, hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>till doth beare a witnes in his breſt.<note place="margin">Conſcientia</note>
            </q>
            <p>S. Paule ſpeaking of the Gentiles, ſheweth that they haue the effect of the Lawe, written in their harts, their con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſciences bearing witnes,<note place="margin">Rom, 2, 15,</note> and as long as we liue in this worlde, God graunt that this witnes may alwayes ſtirre and ſting vs, till we be aſhamed of ſin vnleſſe after this life, it be opened as in an inditement to accuſe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgment ſeate,<note place="margin">Reu. 20, 12</note> as Iohn maketh mention. <hi>And I ſaw the dead both great &amp; ſmall ſtand before God, and the</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">That is their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</note> 
               <hi>bookes were opened, and an other booke was ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which is the booke of life, &amp; the dead were iudged of thoſe thinges which were written in the bookes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their works.</hi> Thus we may
<pb facs="tcp:17676:34"/> ſée the conſcience in thys world that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth, and the conſcience in the worlde to come that condemneth. God grant y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we may in this worlde ſo behaue our ſelues, as with Horace to ſay. <hi>Hic mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ahaeneus esto.</hi> This is a braſen wall when a man may knock his breſte and ſay, I knowe nothing héere that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me aſhamed or a feard.<note place="margin">Miſcellan prelect ſep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time, To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> primi.</note> He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll ſée more of the conſcience, let him looke in the Biſhoppe of Exceter hys booke <hi>Not in Ally,</hi> though indéede he wryte of conſcience at large. But D. <hi>Wolton</hi> that is now Biſhop, who wryte larger in his booke called the Conſcience, dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to a godly zealous knight, S. <hi>Iohn Gilbert,</hi> mine olde good maſter &amp; louing fréend a fit Patrone for ſuch a booke and title, there he ſhal find inough, touching the conſcience.<note place="margin">The third enemy v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſinne,</note> An other moſt terrible enemy vnto mankind for ſinnes ſake, is death, who by reaſon that our bodye is all ſpotted &amp; corrputed with ſinne, hath his lawfull acceſſe vnto mankind, and foloweth him ſtep by ſtep, from place to place, of what eſtate or degrée ſoeuer he bée, either King, Prince, Duke, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, Earle, lord, baron, knight, or whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther he be rich or mighty, wiſe or poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:35"/> tyll at laſt he plucketh him downe, and depriueth him of life, wife, children, hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, lands, goods, and all thoſe thinges in the world, wherin he ſetled his hart. The cauſe of this his power is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man beeing corrupted wyth ſin, is rewarded with death: a certaine appoyntment of God in our firſt parent for his ſin and diſobedience.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, 2.17,</note> As appeareth in Geneſis, <hi>2. In the day that thou eateſt thereof, thou shalt die the death.</hi> In that he dyd eate, he diſobeyed, and ſo ſinned, which ſinne hath runne into all hys poſterity by diſcent hetherto,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 5, 12</note> and ſhall vnto the worlds ende, and that is the cauſe that Death triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pheth ouer vs in this world in ouerthrowing vs. S. Paul ſayth: <hi>Stipendium peccati mors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 6, 23</note> The rewarde of ſinne is death. Likewiſe the Apoſtle Iames ſayth:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 1.15.</note> When luſt hath concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, it bringeth forth ſinne, and ſin whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is finiſhed bringeth foorth death. So that there is no doubt among men, but by reaſon of ſinne death hath taken hold in them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om, 5.12,</note> and as ſin is entred into all the worlde, as the Apoſtle ſayth: euen ſo death is like to run vpon all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are in the world by reaſon of ſinne. But
<pb facs="tcp:17676:35"/> now ſome will obiect, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect </seg>
               </label> that whether wée ſinne much or little, it is all one, for we are aſſured of death thereby, not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the multitude of ſinnes, but (as it were) féeding the inclination of ſinne, knowing that there is but to the one and to the other, a death for a rewarde. But I anſwer,<note place="margin">Reſp.</note> if any man ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon boldly preſume on ſinne, and feede the humor thereof,<note place="margin">Short de terrible. Deu. 30.18.</note> he ſhall not only ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten death vnto him, but alſo plucke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him a moſt terrible death, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in Moſes. If thy hart turne away ſo that thou wylt not obey, but ſhalt bée ſeduced, and worſhippe other Gods and ſerue them, I pronounce vnto you thys day, that ye ſhall ſurely periſh, you ſhal not prolong your daies in the lande. S. Paule charging the Corinthians for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing the ſacrament, ſayd:<note place="margin">1, Co. 11.3</note> For thys cauſe many are ſicke among you, and many fall on ſléepe. And yet it is not a generall rule, that they which are cutte off, that theyr dayes are ſhortned tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ſinne, for Iohn Baptiſt, and the Innocents that were murthered by He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rode are no ſuch examples, for ſuch the Lord dooth not onely take away becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:17676:36"/> they are vnworthy of the worlde, but ſometimes they are arguments of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation vnto their oppreſſers, again in them was not ſéene ſuch manifeſt ſin wherby they did drawe vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods wrath to cut of their dayes, but in thoſe in whom plentifulnes of obſtinate ſin doth raigne, vndoubtedly they ſhorten their dayes, as on the otherſide, they which ſerue the Lord, and followe hys precepts and lawes, their daies ſhalbe prolonged.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, 20,</note> As appeareth in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. Honour thy father and thy mother, that thy daies may be long in the land which the Lord thy God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thée.<note place="margin">K n, 20, 6,</note> Was there not xv. yeeres ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Ezechias in ſeruing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. The prophet Dauid ſaith.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal, 34, 12</note> What man is he that liſteth to liue, &amp; wold faine ſée good daies: kéepe thy tongue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euil, and thy lips that they ſpeake no guile. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame &amp; like wordes hath the Apoſtle Peter, alſo when the Lord appeared vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Salomon in Gibeon,<note place="margin">Pet, 3, 10,</note> and had giuen him the excellency of wiſedom, he adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kin. 3, 14</note> 
               <hi>If thou wilt walk in my waies to keepe my ordinances and my commandements, as thy father Dauid did walk. I wil prolong thy daies.</hi> And
<pb facs="tcp:17676:36"/> yet not only this bleſſing of prolonging of daies ſhalbe giuen to the ſeruaunts of God, but euen in the ende, they ſhall die a peaceable death, as happened to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good king Ioſias, to whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſaid,<note place="margin">2, Ki, 22, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for his good embraſing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke of the Law, and fearing him. Beholde I wyll gather thée to thy fathers, &amp; thou ſhalt be put in thy graue in peace, and thine eies ſhall not ſée all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil which I wyl bring vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this place. O good God, what ſweeter wordes to a chriſtian hart, and what greater ioy to a good conſcience then to depart in peace, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neither God in vengeaunce, nor the worlde in excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay any thing to our charge, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this length of life, nor this peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble death ſhalbe aſſured to the vngodly and wicked, but as I ſaid, their daies ſhalbe cut of, and their end ſhalbe in ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ror &amp; feare, as it appeareth in Ezechiel,<note place="margin">Ezech, 14</note> either by famine, peſtilence, ſworde, or wyld beaſts. Howe terrible was the death of the inhabitants of Sodom and Gomor, O howe lamentable and moſt dreadfull was the ende of Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem when it was ſackt by Tytus and Veſpaſian. Howe fearefull was the end of Iezabell, being rent a ſunder
<pb facs="tcp:17676:37"/> with dogges, and deuoured by peece-meale. How was the ende of rebellious Abſalon, which was caught from hys horſe, and hanged by the haire. Howe odious was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of Antiochus, which putrified and rotted where he lay, that hys Chamberlaine coulde not abide his ſmell. Moſt horrible was the ende of Holophernus, who was beheaded in hys drunken ſléepe, and all theſe wyth a great many more abridged their daies, and ended them in moſt terrible and fearefull manner, and that for their wicked and abhominable lyuing, in moſt deteſtable ſinne and wickednes, ſome in horedome, ſome in pryde, ſome in diſobedience, ſome in extortion, ſome in tyranny and cruell murther, &amp;c. I remember I was by the bedſide of an olde preacher,<note place="margin">Hunting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> who di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n froo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Zel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note> who lay in his death bed, and ſayd vnto me. Euen as the water which is poyſoned, killeth all the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of fiſh in it, ſo I tell thée in thys world, the whole ayre is ſo corrupted with the ſinne of man, that I doubt mée it wyll bring all the world to a confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a ſhort time. I pray God deliuer me, and giue England repentant harts.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:37"/>
            <p>The moſt horrible and moſt fearefull enemy that yet was ſpoken of agaynſte the ſinne of man, is hell,<note place="margin">The laſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to ſinne.</note> a place of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for euer, without releaſe, appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted for ſathan, &amp; all ſuch as haue ſtoutly ſerued him, without veyling theyr ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of repentaunce to almighty God: an enemy ſo dreadfull, as me thinkes the verye remembraunce of ſo terrible a place, ſhould ſéeme to reuoke and drawe backe a ſinner, although he had neuer ſo great a delight in his iourney. A place not onely full of all paynes &amp; torments, but alſo continuing and enduring for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and euer, a place voyde of releaſe, or mitigation of paynes, thether com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neyther mercy nor bayle, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion nor pittye. The lamentable out cryes and ſcriches of them that are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, doo neuer come from thence vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the eares of helpe, or vnto the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of pitty.<note place="margin">Eſa. 30, 33</note> It is deſcribed in the Prophet Eſay, <hi>Topheth</hi> is prepared of olde, it is euen prepared for the King, hée hath made it déepe and large, the burning thereof is fire &amp; much woode, the breath of the Lorde like a fire of Brimſtone doth kindle it. He ſpeaketh
<pb facs="tcp:17676:38"/> figuratiuely, that as the ſtate of heauen in many places of the new Teſtament is ſet forth by ſimilituds, becauſe other wiſe we cannot conceiue of it, euen ſo hell in this place is called <hi>Topheth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Topheth</note> which was a vallye of the children of Hinnom néere Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">2, Ki, 23, 10</note> where the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were ſacrificed to <hi>Moloch</hi> which was a great Image of braſſe,<note place="margin">Lyra.</note> proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned like vnto a man, and being holow within, it ſhould firſt be made fire redde hote, and when the child ſhoulde be put into it and cloſed vp, then the prieſtes would make ſuch a noiſe with Targets and timbrels, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parents ſhould not heare the voice of the infant, whereby they myght be moued to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but beléeue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the infant died peaceably with out paine, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Gods did preſently receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule of the infant: this was their abhominable Idolatrye, in thys vally néere Ieruſalem, which yet is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led <hi>Ben-hinnom,</hi> which is aſmuch to ſay by interpretation as the ſonne of <hi>Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom,</hi> afterward for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> filthy abuſe of the place, &amp; for the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt therof <hi>Ioſiah</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed dead carions to be caſt there. Nowe <hi>Topheth</hi> taketh his deriuation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Toph</hi> which ſignifieth <hi>Timphanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> a Tabret,<note place="margin">Pſa. 81,</note> or
<pb facs="tcp:17676:38"/> dromſlade which they vſed as I ſaid, in this vally, to take away the pittiful cry of the child, frying in this Images hote hollow place. And in our owne capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we ſée a certaine deſcription of hell by this figure, a place full of torments, in the which the tormented ſhall ſuffer ſuch paines,<note place="margin">Mat, 13, 42</note> as ſhall prouoke wéeping and gnaſhing of teeth, yea ſuch as are intollerable, on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> otherſide, the children of God, ſhall not be moued to compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to behold them, no although they ſée their father, mother, children, kinſfolke or ſuch like, for as the Tabret, and tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brell tooke away the childs cry in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol <hi>Moloch,</hi> ſo ſhall the ioy and ſwéete melody of heauen, ſtop their pittye or compaſſion of them which ſhall dwell in heauen. And although this ſimilitude holdeth not in all parts to the reaſon of them, that would diſcourſe vpon it, yet ſo farre it holdeth, as we muſt conceiue the matter, although we omit the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. As the vally of Hinnom was a place néere Ieruſalem, wherein after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Ioſiah</hi> cauſed all the filth and cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the citty to be layd, as fit for no better thing, becauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horrible abuſe and Idolatry therin ſometimes doone.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:39"/>
            <p>Euen ſo the heauenly Ieruſalem doth purge it ſelfe of all thoſe filthy carions, I meane the reprobate that ſtincke of their ſinne, before the face of God, and are ordayned to bee caſte out into thys <hi>Topheth</hi> as a place fitte for ſuch a receypt.</p>
            <p>Nowe as there is a damnable place, wherin the fire is neuer quenched, and the worme neuer dyeth. Euen ſo there are ſome men, whoſe ſinnes are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp; offences ſo greate, that neuer ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the grace and fauour of almightye God, neuer repent them of their ſins, theſe (I ſay) ſhalbe poſſeſſors and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritours of thys place of torments,<note place="margin">Math. 13.41, 42,</note> as our ſauiour Chriſt ſayth: The ſonne of man ſhall ſende foorth hys Angels, and they ſhall gather out of his kingdome all thinges that offend, and them which doo iniquity, and ſhall caſt them into a Fornace of fire, there ſhalbe wayling and gnaſhing of téeth. Lykewiſe Saint Paule to the Hebrewes. If we ſinne wyllingly,<note place="margin">Heb, 10, 26, 27,</note> after that we haue receiued the knowledge of the trueth, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth no more ſacrifice for ſinnes, but a fearefull looking for of iudgement
<pb facs="tcp:17676:39"/> and violent fire, which ſhal deuoure the aduerſaries. Alſo it is ſayd in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde Epiſtle of Peter.<note place="margin">2, Pe, 2, 9.</note> The Lorde knoweth to deliuer the godly out of temptation, and to reſerue the vniuſt vnto the daye of iudgement to be puniſhed. Alſo in S. Iohn hys Reuelation.<note place="margin">Reu. 20, 15,</note> And who ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was not found in the Booke of life, was caſt into the Lake of fire. Howe woefull and terrible ſhall the dreadfull day of iudgement bee vnto the wycked and reprobates, when Chriſt Ieſus ſhall ſit and make diuiſion the Goates from the Shéepe, when he ſhall ſay to the ſhéepe. <hi>Come yee bleſſed, receyue the kingdome prepared for you &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math, 25 34</note> And to the Goats, that is to ſay, the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked, he ſhal ſay,<note place="margin">Verſe, 41,</note> 
               <hi>Depart from me ye cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed into euerlaſting fire, which is prepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red for the deuill and his aungells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherfore while we are héere in thys worlde, let vs with terror beholde the dreadfull ſentence of damnation, &amp; with all diligence and care, call our ſelues to account,<note place="margin">Eph, 5,</note> redéeming and purchaſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the time which we haue wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſpent, and become not onely new, but ſtedfaſt members, and then, if thy hand
<pb facs="tcp:17676:40"/> or eye cauſe thée to offend, cut them off, and caſt them from thée.<note place="margin">Mat, 18, 8, 9,</note> It is better for thée to enter into life halt, maymed, or blind, then hauing two handes, two féete, or two eyes, to be caſt into hell fire. And becauſe ſathan goeth on ſtyll ſo buſily with his worke, and all the world in a manner ſéemeth wyllinglye to be his workmanſhip. It is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that now, euen nowe, we reclaime our ſelues, according to the caueat of the Euangeliſt. Nowe is the axe layde to the roote of the trées,<note place="margin">Luk. 3.9,</note> therefore euery trée which bringeth not foorth good fruit ſhalbe hewen downe, and caſt into the fire.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I bréefely layde downe the moſt gréeuous enimies to mankind which preuaile the more againſt him, by reaſon of the ſinne which he ſéemeth to nouriſh, and make ripe in his ready wyll, and wylling inclination. I would it mought be ſo ſurueyed, that it may be lothed, and ſo lothed, that it may bée th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oughly mortified, wherby theſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies may not ſo lay ſiege vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule of man, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende, he may be taken captiue, and led to an vnbailable gaole, the Lord grant it for his Chriſtes ſake.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:40"/>
            <head>The prayer.</head>
            <p>O Lord God, full of all pittie &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſsion, looke downe vppon vs miſerable wretches and ſinners, who are not onely laden &amp; ouerladen with the multitude of ſinnes and wickednes but are ready to be ſwallowed vp and vtterly deſtroyed, vnles thou of thy pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and mercy, which haue beene euer of olde, vouchſafe to gard and defend vs, for the enimies are at hand ready to ouerthrow vs, thy vengeaunce han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ouer our heads, ready to fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, our conſcience burneth in vs, ready to conſume vs. Death wayteth daylie vpon vs, and calleth vs, hel gate is open, and we ſhall be vtterly conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. If thou O moſt mercifull God extend not thine accuſtomed fauoure. Although we haue ſinned O Lord, and that moſt greeuous in thy ſight, wee are hartely ſorry for it, and foraſmuche as thou requireſt a humble harte, and a penitent minde, accept O Lord, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunt teares of thy humble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts, and vouchſafe to reſtore thy Iſraell agayne which hath gone a
<pb facs="tcp:17676:41"/> a ſtray and though we bee wylling to caſt away our ſelues, yet O Lorde bee thou our guyde and director, we ſee not the deepenes of our owne ſinne, not yet the ſweetenes of thy mercy, nor yet the bitternes of the ſcourges, which thou haſt ordeyned for ſinne, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our eyes O Lord and giue vs thy holy ſpirite to mollifie our harts that we may wholy become thine, &amp; ſaue vs for thy mercy ſake at the laſt, for ſyn is ſo rype, and the time ſo corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that vengeaunce is at hand, and when it is ready to fall, we are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to abide it, wherefore O Lord call thy whole flock ſpeedily, and deliuer them out of Sodome, as thou diddeſt thy ſeruaunt Lot, that they may not be partakers with the infidels, which know not thy name, nor come when thou calleſt, but are gon to the worlde, and followed the concupiſcence of their owne harts. Graunt vnto vs O Lorde, the ſweete conſolation of thy ſpirite, for Ieſus Chriſt hys ſake. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="explanation">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:41"/>
            <head>How we ſhall in Chriſt Ieſu, take away the force and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of ſin, and remooue the ſiege of thoſe enemies aforeſayde, and howe we ſhall become good Chriſtians.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He meane howe we ſhall reforme our ſelues,<note place="margin">Cap, 4,</note> take away the force of ſinne, and to cauſe almightye God to become our good and merci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull father &amp; protector, omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſacrifice of Chriſt, which is all in all, and ſhewing our owne duety. I wyll lay downe in theſe ſixe poynts. <hi>1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">6, Thinges learned ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth vs new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in a chriſtian ſhape.</note> We muſt looke into our creation and ſée what we are, and what we ſhould bée. <hi>2.</hi> We muſt heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, and what is to be gathered out of it. <hi>3.</hi> Wée muſt vſe harty prayer. <hi>4.</hi> Wée muſt ſuffer affliction. <hi>5.</hi> Forſake the world and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh. <hi>6.</hi> We muſt looke in to the ſwéetenes of the ſecond life: and all theſe béeing wel looked into as they are, and as I purpoſe by Gods grace effectually &amp; briefely to lay them down ſhall bee inough for a chriſtian man to learne for his office and duety.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:42"/>
            <p>The firſt thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ought to looke into, and the firſt leſſon that we ſhoulde learne is, to knowe our creation and forme, not our quallities and diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that by the view thereof, we ſhould in all behauiour ſhewe, that neither in mind or in action, which is agréeable to our title, name, calling and kinde, that as we are the image of God, ſo wee ſhould frame our ſelues to that ſhape of godlines, and as wee are reaſonable creatures, ſo we ſhould vſe our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with vnderſtanding, and as wée haue the dominion ouer all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſo we ſhould kéepe our honour and eſtimation, not communicating with them. So long we be men, and ſo long we kéepe the honour of our kinde, as we vſe our ſelues not only after the Lawe of God, but at leaſt wiſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law of nature, for we are endued with a reaſonable ſoule and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite,<note place="margin">Heb, 4, 12</note> not to affect wicked, ſinfull, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiliſh thinges, nor yet to will &amp; deſire thinges that are againſt the glorye of God, for if God be glorified in his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, euen ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more we oughte to ſet forth his glory, by how much hée hath exalted vs aboue all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb facs="tcp:17676:42"/> with true holines, with perfecte charity, with ſound knowledge, with continuall deuotion, with thankes gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, with equity, with mercy, and ſo foorth, as it becommeth a man endued with a reaſonable ſoule, againe, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he hath ſette vs aboue all hys handy workes, and hath ſet all thinges in ſubiection vnder our féete, let vs not looſe that honor and dignity, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come brute beaſtes our ſelues in our behauiour, but rather as I ſayd be like men, as we are created, and kéepe the image of God in perfect knowledge, iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtice and temperance, ſanctification and holines, according as the Apoſtle ſayth. This is the wyll of God,<note place="margin">1, Theſſa. 3, 4</note> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſanc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tification, and that we ſhould abſtayne from fornication, that euery one of you ſhould knowe howe to poſſeſſe his veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in holines and honour, but aſſoone as we giue ouer a holye conuerſation, a reaſonable ſpirite, a chaſt minde, and a good behauiour, then wee fall into beaſtly behauiour, and brutiſh maners, and from men quickly become beaſtes, and called by the name of beaſtes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then from reaſon wée fall euen to the corruption of nature and luſtes
<pb facs="tcp:17676:43"/> thereof, and doo not ſée the violation of Gods commandement, defacing of our image, nor the ouerthrow of our honor. Therefore is it,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, 2.12</note> that the Apoſtle calleth vs beaſts, ſaying: But theſe as brute beaſtes, led with ſenſuality, and made to be taken and deſtroyed, ſpeake euill of thoſe thinges which they know not, and ſhall perriſh through their own cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruption.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 10, 14</note> Likewiſe the Prophet Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſayth. Euery man is a beaſt by hys owne knowledge. Horace in his tyme called the people of Rome for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy, and vnſtablenes, and chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able deſires.<note place="margin">Epiſto.</note> 
               <hi>Bellua multorum capitum.</hi> A beaſt of many heads: there are many (which for their affections and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in ſcripture, are called beaſts, ſome by the name of a Lyon for his tyranny.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anny.</note> Of ſuch the prophet Dauid ſpake, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he did flée to the Lord for ſuccor, ſaying: O my God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 7, 1, 2,</note> in thée haue I put my truſt ſaue me from all them that perſecute me, and deliuer my ſoule, leaſt he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure my ſoule like a Lyon, and teare it in péeces while there is none to help. Such we haue not a ſmall ſtore in Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande, which through tyranny and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion haue deuoured many a poore
<pb facs="tcp:17676:43"/> ſoule, and eate them out of houſe, liuing and all, and may well be called Lyons, for in their tyranny as they haue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion nor pitty,<note place="margin">Scorpion flattery</note> ſo who dare of all the beaſts in the field, to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lambe out of the lions clawes, and what man dare ſpeake or controll ſome of our lyons for their pray. Some are called Scorpions for ſtinging vnder the ſhew of faire flat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tering, as the prophet Ezechiel,<note place="margin">Ezech, 2, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> béeing wylled to ſpeake vnto a ſtout harted na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, ſhould not feare them, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten. And thou ſon of man, feare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, neither be afraid of their wordes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though rebels &amp; thornes be with thee, &amp; thou remaineſt with ſcorpions, feare not their lookes &amp;c. The nature of the ſcorpion is thus deſcribed,<note place="margin">Plini et Barth, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Blandiuntur facie ſed cauda pungunt acute,</hi> they flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet with their face, but they ſting wyth their tayle, many a faire word, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a faire ſhew hath deceiued many an honeſt Engliſh hart, ſwéetely pypeth the fowler, when the poore byrd goeth to wrack, many a faire promiſe, louing looke, and bidding to bankets, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued many a one of his liuing, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued many a one of his life burdened ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny a one with cares, I wyl not ſay, that
<pb facs="tcp:17676:44"/> in cauſes of marriage by faire wordes many a one hath béene deceiued, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the poore old widdowes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> race,</note> 
               <hi>Sunt qui fruſtis et pomis viduas venentur aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yne for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hines,</note> Some are called Swine for their filthines, and ſluttiſh wallowing in the dunghill of luſt, and for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they eſtéeme not their owne clenlines, as appeareth in Mathew.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, 7, 6</note> Caſt not pearles before ſwyne. And as S. Peter ſayth. The ſowe that was waſhed,<note place="margin">Pe, 2, 22</note> is returned to the wallowing in the myre, and wee that haue béene waſhed in the fountain of Chriſtianity, are returned into the puddell of adultery and filthy fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if this deformed ſhape, were ſéene in forme, as it is knowne in deſire in all the worlde, there be a great many magiſtrates and Officers, yea and ſuch as be ſhepheardes myght be aſhamed to ſée that nowe they are ſwyneheards. Brybery affection and negligence hath (the more pitty) engendred to manye ſwyne in theſe dayes. Some are called by the name of Bulls,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Oxen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Kine theyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſsion</note> Oxen, and Kine, for their oppreſſion and cruelty, &amp; they are ſaid to be of Baſhan, which was an hill of excellent paſture in the Country
<pb facs="tcp:17676:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> néere Iordan, wher Og was King. A ſignification in thoſe whoſe bellyes bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full, are moſt cruell &amp; fierce againſt the poorer ſort.<note place="margin">Pſal, 22,</note> The Prophet Dauid cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out againſt them ſaying, Many Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en are come about me, fatte Buls of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan cloſe me in on euery ſide. Likewyſe the Lord himſelf cryeth out againſt them in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> propheſie of Amos.<note place="margin">Amos 4</note> Heare this word ye Kine of Baſhan, that are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Samaria, which oppreſſe the poore and deſtroy the néedy.<note place="margin">Foxe fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubtilty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Some are called by the name of a Fox, for theyr ſubtilty, which is naturally in the Foxe. As appeareth in the Prophet Ezechiell.<note place="margin">Ezech. 1</note> where the Lorde himſelfe cryeth out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſubtilty of the prophets of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, ſaying. O Iſraell, thy prophets are like the foxes in the waſte places. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the Goſpell of Luke, Our ſauiour Chriſt calleth Herode by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name, when the Phariſies came and wylled him to depart, leaſt that he would kil him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them. <hi>Goe and tell that foxe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 1</note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I caſt out deuills, &amp;c.</hi> We haue a great many foxes in England, (God help vs) which kéepe their holes a day time, &amp; goe about miſchiefe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night ſeaſon,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:45"/> many ſubtill practiſes, they imagine in their idle lurking dens, ſome to deſtroye the eſtate, &amp; ſome to alter religion, and ſome to make a confuſion of order, the Lord turne their harts, or ſpéedilye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found them. We haue beſides them a great many hungry foxes that goe about to ſpoyle the poore Lambes of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as the buier &amp; ſeller vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coloure of ſwearing, lying, facing, &amp;c, deceiueth many a ſimple néedy man, eſpecially hée that buieth vpon lende, and cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare, he that buieth of ſuch foxes, ſhall aſſuredly haue the worſt, and pay well for the beſt. But we haue worſe foxes then theſe, that is, our vſurers, for they bite not onely but deuoure vp quite, and their ſubtiltie is to beguile God almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye, and to cozen the law, for they haue no mony of their owne, but can borrow of a fréend, and yet he ſhall haue none of that, but if he wyll take ware, (beware the fox) hee wyll fléece you and ſkin you alſo, and make you pay vii. ſkore for the hundred, before the yere be out, for hee ſaith, it is lawfull to buy and ſell. And yet we haue worſe foxes then theſe, which are ſome of our Lawyers (God forbid I ſhould ſay all) they wyl ſo draw
<pb facs="tcp:17676:45"/> men and win men, wyth their warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of good and ſufficient matter, tyll they haue ſucked out all the blood in his purſe, then they care neither for him nor hys matter. I remember <hi>Iſope</hi> ſpeaketh of ſuch a beaſt, which ſawe the Rauen hauing a péece of chéeſe in his mouth on a trée, to whom this fox ſaid. O what a fayre byrd you are, and how brauely you can ſing, I meruaile men ſay you are a fowle byrd, and a bad ſinger, I promiſe you I like your ſinging of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byrds in the world, with that the Rauen offered to ſing, and opened his mouth, and down fell the chéeſe, which the fox tooke, and ran away with it laughing, and had no more to doo afterward with hys beautye or commendation: neyther haue our Foxes to doo any more wyth mens mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters when they haue the chéeſe.</p>
            <p>Some are called by the name of dogges for their diſdainefullnes and enuye,<note place="margin">Dog for diſdainful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; enuy</note> for that the nature of a dogge is alwaies to diſdaine and enuy his owne kind, as the olde ſaying is
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dum canis os rodit ſociari pluribus edit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhile the dog doth gnaw the bone,</l>
                  <l>He doth deſyre to eate alone.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:46"/>
            <p>For this cauſe he dooth ſhew his ſurfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nature, which is rather then he wil impart to an other, we will ouer charge his owne ſtomacke wyth eating, to hys owne anoyaunce. Therefore it is that Peter ſayth.<note place="margin">1, Pe, 2, 22,</note> The Dog returneth againe to his vomite, to ſéeke phiſicke for his ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feyte, when his belly is ouercharged, for that carying an enuious mind, and a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfull to others, he would rather hurte himſelfe, then leaue any thing to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure others, and for that cauſe they were called alſo dogges by Chriſt, to whome holines was not imparted, partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wold make a ſurfaiting meale of it, kéeping all to themſelues, and yet dooing no good to themſelues, and partlye becauſe they wold not impart to others, when he ſayd,<note place="margin">Math, 7, 6</note> 
               <hi>Gyue not holy thinges vnto dogges.</hi> for that indéede thinges ought to be beſtowed on them that bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite themſelues, and doo good with it vnto others.</p>
            <p>Many more ſuch beaſtes there bee in mens ſhape, as the ſlothfull man is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an Aſſe, the deuourer is called a Woolfe, the ſcornefull, as Eccleſiaſticus ſayth:<note place="margin">Eccl. 33, 6</note> is like an horſe, that neyeth. Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull
<pb facs="tcp:17676:46"/> it is, that <hi>Circe</hi> raigneth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch ſuch men, and to tranſforme them from their honourable eſtate and ſhape of mankind, into the diſfygured ſhew of brute beaſtes, but this happeneth, when men fall from God, and obey their owne appetites, and luſts, then they become bruite beaſtes, that haue no vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and God giueth them vp vnto their owne vile affections. Woe bee vnto that people whom God hath forſaken, but double woe vnto them that fall from their eſtate,<note place="margin">Rom, 1, 26</note> and loſe their ſhape of reaſon vertue, and godlines, and become bruite beaſtes in their dooings, they are ſo diſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured, that he wyll not knowe them at the day of iudgement, from the ſhape of beaſtes.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde meane to take away the force, of ſinne,<note place="margin">2. Poynte</note> is that we muſt heare the word of God, and learne what is to bee gathered out of it, and héerein wee muſt take thys order.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> What the word of God is.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> How we muſt heare it, and vſe it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> What we muſt gather out of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">What the worde of God is.</note> becauſe I wil not ſtand vpon the large definitions &amp; interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:17676:47"/> men. I wyll deliuer out of the ſcripture what the reward of God is.</p>
            <p>Firſte in Deutronomye it is called wiſedome,<note place="margin">Deu, 4, 6,</note> where it is ſaid, Kéepe them therefore and doo them, for that is your wiſedome, and your vnderſtanding in the ſight of the people, which ſhall heare all theſe ordinaunces, and ſhall ſay, onely this people is wiſe, and of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and a great nation. Therefore it is neceſſary that Magiſtrates, councellers, and officers, (who are choſen for theyr wiſedome) ſhoulde learne their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge out of the word of God,<note place="margin">Pſal, 2, 10</note> as Dauid ſaid. Be wiſe now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O ye kinges, be learned ye that are Iudges of the earth, that their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, policy, and gouernement myght, procéede from a godly direction, &amp; from the rule of Gods word, which woulde not onely terrifie the people the more from their folly, but inflame the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a great deale the ſooner with obedience, becauſe it procéedeth from ſo good a fountaine. Alſo the prophet Dauid called it a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne,<note place="margin">A Lanterne or Lyght. Pſa, 119, 105,</note> ſaying: <hi>Thy word O Lorde is a Lanterne vnto my feete, and a light vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my pathes.</hi> that foraſmuch as wee walke in a darke ſinfull world, by the
<pb facs="tcp:17676:47"/> word of God we ſhould be directed how to goe, and which waies, leaſt we knock our ſelues in euery blocke of ſinne, our ſauiour Chriſt by the ſame light, giueth light to them that ſit in darknes,<note place="margin">Luk, 2,</note> and in the ſhadowe of death, and to guyde our féete into the way of peace. What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter comfort vnto trauellers then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day light, and what greater diſcomforte to wayfaring men then the darke night, God be thanked that hath giuen vs the light of hys holy worde, therefore while it is day let vs not harden our hartes, as in the prouocation,<note place="margin">Power of GOD. Rom, 1, 16</note> and in the day of tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation. Likewiſe S. Paule dooth call the word of God the power of God to ſaluation, to euery one that beléeueth, hée ſaith not that it is a ſecrete reuelation, or the Hyſtorye of prophane matters, but that it is the ſame wherein the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power of God is hidden, to helpe ſuccoure, defende and comforte the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeuers.</p>
            <p>Alſo it is called a mighty worker as S. Paule ſayth:<note place="margin">A mighty worker. Hebr. 4, 12,</note> The worde of God is louely and mighty in operation, and ſharper then any two edged ſworde, and
<pb facs="tcp:17676:48"/> entereth through, euen to the deuiding a ſunder of the ſoule and the ſpirite, and of the ioynts and the marowe, and is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerner of the thoughtes, and the intentes of the hart, ſo that as we haue many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies, ſores, byles, aches, and inwarde diſeaſes. Euen ſo God hath ordeined ſuch an excellent oyntment, euen the oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his holy word, to pearce through euery artery, ioynt, ſinewe and bone, to purge vs, eaſe vs, and cure vs. So that nowe what greater comfort then wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to our knowledges, light vnto our darke pathes, defence for our poore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhielded bodies, and health for our ſicke ſoules, which the Lord of his mercy hath imparted vnto vs, by &amp; in his holy word.</p>
            <p>Now it reaſteth howe we heare the word of God and vſe it. Firſt we muſt conſider that we vſe all diligence and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility in hearing the word of God, and put of all phantaſies, cares, heauines, and worldly imaginations, and that wée put on true vnderſtandinge and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as it is ſayde: Hée that recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the ſéede (which is Gods worde) in good ground,<note place="margin">Mat, 13, 23</note> is hée that heareth the
<pb facs="tcp:17676:48"/> word, and vnderſtandeth it. Otherwiſe if we endeuour not to vnderſtand, if the Trumpet ſounde an vncertaine ſounde,<note place="margin">1, Cor. 14, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> who can prepare himſelfe to the battell, there may be a fault in the Trumpettor, there may be a fault in the hearer, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let the one be diligent to teache tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſincerely, let the other heare atten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiuely, and vnderſtand fruitfully, and when we haue ſo doone, it is not inough to learne and to leaue off, but to followe the rule of Moſes in Deutronomy, who ſayth: Theſe wordes which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund thée thys day,<note place="margin">Deu. 6, 6,</note> ſhalbe in thy hart thou ſhalt rehearſe them continually vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy children, and ſhalt talke of them when thou tarrieſt in thy houſe, and as thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lyeſt downe, and when thou ryſeſt vppe, and thou ſhalt bynde them for a ſigne vppon thyne hande, and they ſhall bée as frontlets betwéene thyne eyes, alſo thou ſhalt write them vppon the poſtes of thy houſe, and vppon thy gates.</p>
            <p>It is not inough to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of GOD, but to exerciſe it, to the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vppe of the menne of GOD, and for the preſeruation of hys Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:17676:49"/> in ſafety. The Euangeliſt ſaith, Whoſoeuer heareth the worde of God,<note place="margin">Math. 7, 24</note> and doth the ſame, I will liken him to a wiſe man, which hath builded his houſe on a rocke. But now becauſe there are many doubtes and repugnances in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture that it ſéemeth to be harde and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, which wyll lothe many a man to the reading or hearing of it. It follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that therefore he ſhould be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or ſhrinke backe, for he is wylled to ſéeke and ſhall find, to knocke and it ſhall be opened, and againe on the other ſide, the Lord wyll not leaue his church deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and comfortles, for he willed Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip to ioyne vnto the Eunuch that was doubtfull, he cauſed all his Apoſtles to goe preach in all the worlde, and ſayth that he wyll rayſe vp prophets vnto hys people, yea and hath truely ſayde him ſelfe <hi>Ero vobiſcum,</hi> I wyll be wyth you vnto the worlds ende.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all we muſt conſider what is to be gathered out of the worde of GOD, which is the fruite, and benefite that wée receiue by it. Whereof the firſte is knowledge by the which wee may diſcerne thynges and knowe our crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,<note place="margin">Knowledge</note> and what he hath and dooth for vs,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:49"/> and alſo our owne duty how we ſhould behaue our ſelues in his ſeruice, this knowledge did Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wiſhe, and pray to be increaſed, in the <hi>Colloſians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.10.</note> When he ſayd. For this cauſe we alſo ſince the day we heard of it, ceaſe not to pray for you, and to deſire that ye might be fulfilled, which knowledge of his will in all wiſedome and ſpirituall vnderſtanding. Likewiſe the prophete <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſayth. I deſired mercy,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6 6.</note> and not ſacrifice, and the knowledge of God more then burnt offeringe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond benefite, is fayth, by the which we are aſſured of the promiſes of God,<note place="margin">Fayth.</note> and eternall ſaluation in his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> dooth call it the ground of thinges which are hoped for, and the euidence of thinges which are not ſéene, which is as muche to ſay, as the certaintie of thoſe things to come. That is, acceptation, redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſanctification, euerlaſting life, and the kingdome of heauen, which things we do expecte, and it is the writing or euidence of the ſame hold, and we are perſwaded, that though we are vnwor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thie of our ſelues, of thoſe heauenly
<pb facs="tcp:17676:50"/> riches, and graces to be beſtowed vpon vs, yet by the death of Chriſte Ieſus, and by his onely ſacrifice we ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy them, which writing an euidence of fayth he hath written in our hearts, and ſealed with his owne blood, ſo that as in euery euidence or indenture hold the tenant oweth due loyalty vnto his Lorde, and conſenteth vnto, and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all couenaunts compriſed in the ſame writinges, ſo we ſhould obeye, ſerue, and aſſent vnto the Lorde, and his ſtatutes, and couenauntes. For ſo is the nature of fayth, according vnto the Gréeke word, to aſſent vnto the word of God, and to haue a ſure truſte in God, that he will of his owne mercy perfourme all thoſe thinges that are written in the word of God, ſo that to haue fayth, or to be faythfull, is ſpoken by correlation, that is, that God ſimp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and abſolutely offereth not his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and grace vnto all, but vnto ſuch as doo acknowledge it with thankes gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, accept it with ioyfulneſſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his ſeruauntes in newe obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and then they are called iuſte or ryghteous, by imputation, and
<pb facs="tcp:17676:50"/> therefore it is ſayde. <hi>The iuſte ſhall lyue by fayth.</hi> Nowe becauſe God is knowen to be mercifull,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.17.</note> there be that follow their owne luſtes and appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, and put of from day to day their returning vnto God, buylding ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on fayth, nor yet on Godes mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, but on their owne luſtye wylles and deſires, and that buylding cannot ſtande, neyther can that be a ſufficient pleaſing of God, that is done without fayth. Yea,<note place="margin">Iames.</note> and yet fayth of it ſelfe in ſome poyntes fayleth, that is, where it doth trouble, or is inconſtant,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.21.</note> as for example. <hi>The Diuels beleeue but they tremble.</hi> Agayne. <hi>Not euery one that ſayth vnto mee Lorde, Lorde, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen, but he that doth the will of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in heauen.</hi> But this fayth fayleth,<note place="margin">Howe ye ſhall know true fayth.</note> becauſe it taſteth of weakeneſſe, feare, and ſynne. The true fayth is tryed by conſtancie in Trybulation, as appeareth in Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the Theſſalonians,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 3.5</note> and by perfecte Loue as appeareth in Saint Paull to Timothye, where
<pb facs="tcp:17676:51"/> he ſayth. <hi>The ende of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement is loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>out of a pure hart, and of a good conſcience, and of fayth vnfayned.</hi> The true fayth hath a frée acceſſe vnto God with boldneſſe.<note place="margin">Eph. 3.12.</note> By true fayth we reſiſt the Diuell, and ouercome the world,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5.4.</note> as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith. This is the victory that ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the worlde, euen our fayth: And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 58.9.</note> your aduerſary the Diuell goeth about like a roring Lion, ſéeking whom he may deuour, whom reſiſt ſtedfaſt in fayth, by true fayth we are preſerued vnto ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith. Which are kept by the power of God through fayth vnto ſaluation.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.5.</note> After all this we muſt conſider that as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge goeth before fayth, ſo perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſtedfaſt continuance, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after fayth, which ſtedfaſt continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance hath béen founde in all the godlye Patriarches,<note place="margin">Perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> Prophets, and Apoſtles, vnremooueable, and which is ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in a chriſtian man, and ſo muche required in a Chriſtian man, as fruit is expected of the trée, without the which the trée is not eſtéemed, for it is the tryall of a man in temptation, or
<pb facs="tcp:17676:51"/> affliction. For the Diuell will ſéeke to remooue hym, the world will ſéeke to ſhake him, the fleſh wil ſeke to weigh his Anker, then if he be vnſtedfaſt, or if he be not founde to be the good figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſouldier of Chriſt, what auayleth all his chriſtian doctrine, yea wat auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his ſworde and buckler, if he run away from his aduerſarie, as <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Demoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> hauing written in his Target. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> good fortune, as who woulde ſay, fortune was his guide, yet in the face of his enemie he ranne away, ſo that whether it be in proſperitie to hold faſt the Lord, and not to be vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puffed vp in the worlde, nor to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle his heart in the world, nor to turne his eies away from his poore brethren, not to oppreſſe, nor couet or deſire an other mans goods, This is ſtedfaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in the Lorde in proſperitie. Or whether it be in aduerſitie to be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in all tribulations to be thankefull for all croſſes, and to tarrie the Lordes leaſure, to ſuffer euery burden that is layde vpon hym, whether it be ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, pouertie, impriſonment, ſlander, or whatſoeuer. Chriſt ſayde, <hi>He that
<pb facs="tcp:17676:52"/> wyll be my diſciple, muſt take vp his croſſe and follow me.</hi> He ſayd not take his croſſe and ſtande ſtyll, or goe backe, but to followe hym, this is ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt fayth in aduerſity. As touching his perſecution which is, that we ſhoulde not ſlyde backe from almightie God, there are many notable examples in ſcripture of it.<note place="margin">Ioſu. 1.8</note> 
               <hi>Ioſuah</hi> ſayth. Let not this booke of the lawe depart out of thy mouth, but meditate therein day and night, that thou mayeſt obſerue and do according to all that is written in it. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth, in his fyrſt Pſalme.<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.12</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man that hath not walked in the counſell of the vngodly. &amp;c. But his delight is in the lawe of the Lord, and in his lawe will he exerciſe hym ſelfe day and night. Iob</hi> ſayth. Although he kyll me I will not forſake hym. Our Sauiour Chriſt ſayth, happie is he that continueth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ende. By the lawe of reaſon we ought ſo long to be the Lordes,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.13</note> as the Lord is ours, but Chriſt Ieſus is ours yeſterday, and to day, and for euer, he findeth vs euery day, comforteth vs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day, ſendeth to vs his grace euery
<pb facs="tcp:17676:52"/> day, encreaſeth his bleſſinges on the earth for vs euery day. Euen ſo euery day we ſhould be faythfull and ſtedfaſt ſeruauntes vnto hym.<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.33</note> The Prophete <hi>Dauid</hi> deſireth the Lord to teach hym the waye of his ſtatutes, and he would kéepe it vnto the ende.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe benefites, knowledge,<note place="margin">New birth Phil. 1.</note> faith, and perſeueraunce, which we ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the word of God, we fynde the regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the new byrth or new ſhaping of our ſelues, for that in déede we were diſfigured by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Adams fall, and loſt the ſhape of righteouſnes, &amp; true obedience, which now in Chriſt are accepted, and nowe we ſhoulde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion our ſelues not according to <hi>Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> in diſobedience, &amp; the luſt of the fleſh, but according to the children of God, and like our forerunner Chriſt Ieſu, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">1. Pe. 1.23.</note> Let the ſame mind be in you, that was in Chriſt Ieſu. Of this newe birth the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. Being borne a newe not of mortall ſéede, but of immortall, by the worde of GOD who lyueth and endureth for euer. O what great comforte
<pb facs="tcp:17676:53"/> do the decayed members of <hi>Adam</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue by the word of God, when by reading or hearing it, they ſée their reſtitution in Chriſt Ieſu, how muche we are bound to almightie God for his worde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Peace.</note>Alſo in the worde of God we finde peace, euen that peace which is conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God to vs ward. Which as the Apoſtle ſayth.<note place="margin">Ep. 2.13.14,</note> 
               <hi>Paſſeth all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> for as much as he was to ſtoute an enemie to be ſet agaynſt vs, &amp; great was our ouerthrowe where he was an aduerſary, and there our Citie was like to be ſackte, and we confounded in our dwellinges. Where the Lorde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged it, but nowe in Chriſt Ieſus, ye which were once farre of, are made néere by the blood of Chriſt. For he is our peace which hath made of both one and hath broken the ſtop of the partiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wall. And he hath commaunded his diſciples that into what Cittie,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.13.</note> towne, or houſe ſo euer that is worthie that they came into, their peace ſhoulde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e vpon it. This peace if it be well weied and well conſidered, what the value of it is, it ſhalbe eſtéemed the moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:17676:53"/> iewel that can be hid in our mind, and the ſwéeteſt ambaſſage that euer was ſent vnto mankinde, for the great accuſation that was layde agaynſt vs, is nowe pacified, and God is at peace with vs.</p>
            <p>An other benefite we gather out of the word of God, which is conſolation,<note place="margin">Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> that is to ſay, the comforte, ioye, and delight of the minde, and the lifting vp of the heart from the oppreſſing cares, the burden of ſinne, and tormentes of this miſerable lyfe. The Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> being plunged in many miſeries, and broyles, ſayde. In the woorde of the Lorde will I reioyce, in the worde of the Lord will I comforte mée.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.92</note> Alſo in the <hi>.119. Pſalm. Except thy law had been my delight, I ſhould nowe haue periſhed in mine afliction.</hi> And againe in the ſame Pſalme <hi>.111.</hi> verſe. Thy teſtimonies haue I taken as an heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for euer, for they are the ioy of my heart. And ſo vndoubtedly in our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame miſerie, in our baniſhment, in our ſicknes, and article of death, when affection is quite deade, and naturall appetite and digeſtion gone, yet the
<pb facs="tcp:17676:54"/> worde of God being reade or hearde is a great comforte and conſolation vnto the minde.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third meane in Chriſt to vanquish the force of ſinne.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3. Meane. Prayer.</note>The thirde meane to vanquiſh the force of ſinne, is humble &amp; hartie pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, not ſuch as procéedeth a <hi>primori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus laboris.</hi> From the téeth forward, but ſuche as commeth from the very heart ſtringes, and féeling of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is the ſame that pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the gates of heauen, and knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the eares of the Lord, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome haue called it the meſſenger betwéene God and man,<note place="margin">Ang. ſee. 26 de tempore. Chriſ, ſup. 22. Nath.</note> ſome the keye of heauen, and ſome the ſtrength of man. Yet for mine owne experience, I acknowledge this definition. <hi>Prayer is the acknowledging of ſin, the feeling of the burthen of conſcience, the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s helples truſt, &amp; the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to gods mercy.</hi> By the which I ſée myne owne weakeneſſe. I confeſſe myne owne neceſſitie, and I flye vnto hym that is the onely helpe, but the manner howe we all ſhoulde flée vnto
<pb facs="tcp:17676:54"/> hym, is, that as he is a ſpirite him ſelfe, ſo in ſpirite we ſhould come vnto him, we vſe not to haue a Clowne of the Countrie, or an Huſbandma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be our atturney in the common lawes of this realme, but a Lawyer, and ſuch a one as may lawfully haue acceſſe to the pleading place, euen ſo in ſpirite and ſoule, which is the ſeate of knowledge, we ſhoulde come vnto the Lorde, for the ſoule is that part of man that ſéeth, knoweth, and affecteth the beſt.<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.1</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> when he prayed vnto the Lorde ſayde, <hi>Vnto thee O Lorde will will I lyft vp my ſoule.</hi> and the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſayde. My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirite hath reioyſed in God my ſauiour. So that the ſpirite muſt labor, the conſcience muſt feele, and the heart muſt flée vnto the almighty, and none other. A good example was ſhewed in <hi>Dauid</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayd.<note place="margin">Pſal. 86.4</note> Comfort the ſoule of thy ſeruaunt, for vnto thée (O Lord) do I lift vp vp my ſoule. Likewyſe in an other place he ſayth. <hi>O let me heare thy louing kindneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes in the morning, for in thee</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17676:55"/> is my truſt, ſhewe thou me the way that I ſhoulde walke in, for I lift vp my ſoule vnto thée, and this is not to be vſed only for neceſſities ſake, when any occaſion or extremitie doth vrge vs, but continually as our Sauiour Chriſt doth warne vs,<note place="margin">Luke. 21, 36</note> ſaying. Watche therefore, and pray continually, that ye may be accompted worthie to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape all theſe thinges that ſhall come to paſſe.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.12.</note> Likewyſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> ſayth. <hi>Reioycing in hope, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient in tribulation, continuing in praier.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 6.18.</note> Alſo in the .vi. to the <hi>Epheſians. Pray alwaies with all maner prayer, and ſupplication in the ſpirite,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof, as long as we are in the fleſhe, ſubiect to miſerie and ſinne, and as longe as Sathan and the fleſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth alwaies to ſtirre, or prouoke vs to ſin, ſo long ſhould we be carefull, and diligent to continue in prayer.</p>
               <p>So that nowe to knowe what pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is, is neceſſary and howe to vſe it is more requiſite, and what is got by it, and what effect it worketh. We may ſée by good examples in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in ſcripture.</p>
               <div type="explanation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:17676:55"/>
                  <head>The effect of prayer.</head>
                  <p>The Lorde ſayth by the Prophete <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15. 1. Kin. 18.45 1. Sam. 1.20</note> Call vpon me in the dayes of thy trouble, and I will deliuer thée. <hi>Eliah</hi> prayed for rayne, and it was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned. <hi>Hannah</hi> being barren, prayed vnto the Lorde for a child, and ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and bare a ſonne, whom ſhe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Samuell. Iehoahaz</hi> being deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the hands of the <hi>Sirians,</hi> for his wickedneſſe, was by prayer deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red agayne from the King of <hi>Aram. Salomon</hi> prayed,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 13.4.</note> and obtayned wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. When all <hi>Bethulia</hi> with the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders therein, coulde by no meanes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue the ſiege of <hi>Holophernes,</hi> with his mightie hoſt. By <hi>Iudithes</hi> prayer, her hand was ſtrengthened, and obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the victory.<note place="margin">Nu. 16.14.18.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aaron</hi> in the time of Plague, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the people, and the Plague ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. When <hi>Ioſua</hi> fought agayng the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mellekites,</hi> he did vanquiſh them, not ſo much by his owne might and policy, as by the continuall prayer of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exo. 12.</note> who as long as he helde vp his handes vnto god, ſo long did <hi>Iſrael</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he faynted &amp; let downe
<pb facs="tcp:17676:56"/> his hands, then did <hi>Ameleck,</hi> and his people preuaile. In ſo much that <hi>Aron</hi> and <hi>Hur,</hi> ſtayed vp his handes till the going downe of the ſonne, otherwiſe they had béen put to flight &amp; diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fited.<note place="margin">Ioſua. 10.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioſua</hi> cauſed the ſonne to ſtaye hys courſe one whole day. At the beſéeging of <hi>Gibeon,</hi> when he made his prayer to almightie God.</p>
                  <p>Thus we ſée prayer to be a meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from man vnto God, and worketh moſt effectually in the faythfull and humble minded man,<note place="margin">4. meane. To forſake the world &amp; the fleſh.</note> as it hath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in theſe places, and in manye moe expreſſed in the holy ſcriptures.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth meane in Chriſt, to vanquish the force of ſinne.</head>
               <p>An other meane for vs to vſe that ſinne may with leſſe force take hold in vs, is to forſake the worlde, &amp; the fleſh, and the Diuell, according vnto our firſt promiſe made vnto God in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, for ſo mightie are thoſe enimies in mans inclination, that they remoue his good affections, and leade hym to a kinde of vayne delite &amp; wicked affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo mightie is this world, eſpecially with his contentes, and the fleſhe with
<pb facs="tcp:17676:56"/> her deſires, that hardly can a man looke vpward, whoſe eyes are fixed downeward, and ſcarce can a man bée of God, whoſe felicitie is ſet eyther in the fleſh, or in the world. An innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable offences it doth cauſe to be prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and many vertues and honeſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therby are quite extinguiſhed, and becauſe I haue ſpoken heretofore of Sathan and of the fleſh, I will nowe onely ſpeake of the world, as one of the mightieſt enimies that man hath in theſe dayes, for by it the worde of God is little regarded, and for the loue of it the Sabbaoth is the more prophaned, by reaſon wherof iuſtice is corrupted, truth is baniſhed, charitie is colde, pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is remoued from mens harts, fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip faynteth, and naturall affection is quit altered, agayne by it, blindnes ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, lyes are vſed, periury is ſuffered, honors are deſired, offices are bought, blynd bayard is a good horſe, &amp; a ſlowe Iade is a good Gelding, by it manhoode is not regarded, chaſtitie is not eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, worldly mariags, &amp; vnfit matches are not gainſaid, vertue had in ſmall price, truſt is had in litle eſtimation,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:57"/> and learning in no accompt, we ſée that for the wordes ſake, naturall loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the father and the childe is alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For the father that is a worldling accompteth not of that childe that is liberall, no although his liberalitie be godly and commendable beſtowed on the poore, and howe many do preferre their children to learning for the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie ſake, or to the law for iuſtice ſake, or to any faculty for the ſame faculties ſake, but rather becauſe they ſhall liue, and beare a countenance in the world. On the other ſide, we ſée the good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the childe chaunged, for whome the father hath taken great paynes, trauelled much, watched often, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure liuinges vnto hym, he thinketh to long the father doth lyue, euery daye wiſheth his death, to haue his goodes and liuing, beſides that, what going to lawe, and mortal hatred betwixt fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of néereſt kinrede, &amp; all for the world. A freend chaungeth his frendſhip in reſpect of the worlde, and ſo long as the other hath, he is a freend, and when he hath nothing, then is he gone, and his frendſhip beginneth to diſſemble, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:57"/> tal men, honeſt men, truſty men, &amp; ſuch as haue good qualities not eſtéemed, if they haue no worldly ſhewe with all, many a one haue ſhut vp his compaſſion from the poore, putting on vngodlyneſſe, lying and ſwearing, that theſe things and theſe they haue giuen alredie, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers waies they are charged, which is very oftentimes an vntruth, many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of Chriſtian profeſſion, hid their wicked actions, and are lyke <hi>Cleophas</hi> they go with Chriſte but they knowe hym not. It is not without cauſe that <hi>Eſdras</hi> ſayde that the world was ful of vnrighteouſneſſe and wickednes,<note place="margin">2. Eſd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.27</note> and becauſe of the ſin and wickedneſſe of the world, the Lord hath Propheſied vnto the world a mighty curſe in <hi>Eſa</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. And therefore as the Apoſtle ſayth.<note place="margin">Eſa. 24.1</note> Loue not the world, neyther the thinges that are in the worlde, if any man loue the world, the loue of the father is not in hym, for all that is in the world (as the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of lyfe) is not of the father,<note place="margin">1. Io. 2.15 6.</note> but is of the world. There is an olde ſaying, <hi>Vide homo ne ſic hereas, vt cum mundo pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as.</hi> Take héede man,<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> that thou ſticke not
<pb facs="tcp:17676:58"/> ſo to the world that thou periſh with the world. The young man in the goſpel had fulfilled all the commaundementes,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.21.</note> and was deſirous of the kingdome of heauen, but when Chriſt bid hym go ſell all that he had, and giue it to the poore, it touched his delight, wherefore Saint <hi>Barnard</hi> ſayth. <hi>Durus est hic ſermo.</hi> &amp;c. This ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſéemeth very harde. Sel all that thou haſt. &amp;c. But yet it is a hard ſaying whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſhall ſay. <hi>Goe ye wicked into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting fire.</hi> The great loue of the worlde as I haue ſayde, is the cauſe of much ſinne, as couetouſneſſe, oppreſſion, extortion, vſury, wreſting of iuſtice, and putting poore men from their right, and their thirſt is ſo great, that a great many will breake their bellies, then leaue or moderate their luſt, they be lyke the flye in a Tarre-barrell, the more he ſtirres, the faſter he is. They are not lyke the Dogges of <hi>Egipt,</hi> which running by the ryuer <hi>Nilus,</hi> and being thirſty, will but lappe, and begone for feare the <hi>Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles</hi> take them, but theſe worldlinges wil ſo long lap, tyl the Diuel hath wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped them vp, they force neyther for the feare of Sathan, nor the fauour of God.
<pb facs="tcp:17676:58"/> Saint Iames ſayth.<note place="margin">Iames. 4.4</note> Who ſo euer wil be a fréend of the world, maketh hym ſelfe an enimie of God, we daylie ſée how lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil be at charges for gods glory, in mayntaining preaching, or in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp ſchollers, nay, they will rather take away both preachers and ſchollers liuinges from them, then adde any thing to it. It is a pittiful matter to ſée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ruſticke worldlinges, for ſome murmure at charitie, ſome grudge at ſubſtance, ſome ſtrayne at the charges of ſouldiers, not looking into the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and eaſe of it, but thinke they haue a gut drawen out of their body, when they haue a pennie taken out of their purſes. For theſe purpoſes, and I thinke they haue cauſe to grudge ſometimes, becauſe their charge is the greateſt burthen, though they be the pooreſt iades.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The .v. meane in Chriſt, to vanquish the force of ſinne.</head>
               <p>When two valued thinges of like quantitie ſhalbe layde together that are of eſtimation, as gold and ſiluer,<note place="margin">The ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the ſecond lyfe,</note> will not euery man make choyſe rather of the gold then of the ſiluer? Nay rather if ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing and nothing, or good and bad were
<pb facs="tcp:17676:59"/> ſet together, would there not be an eaſie choyſe: I make no leſſe differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwixt heauen and earth, this lyfe, and the lyfe to come. For in the one there is miſery, ſorow afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tribulation, diſdayne, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt, malice, ſlaunder, infamie, enuie, pouertie, nakedneſſe, ſickenes, and death. In the other there is ioy, felicitie, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, helth, ſufficiencie, company amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the whole felowſhip of heauen, &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting lyfe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.1.2</note> touching the deſcription of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of ioy, <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth. O howe amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are thy dwellinges thou Lorde of hoſtes, My ſoule hath a deſire and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to enter into the courts of the Lord.<note place="margin">Eſa. 35 10</note> Likewiſe the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſayth. The redéemed of the Lord, ſhall come to <hi>Zion</hi> with prayſe, and euerlaſting ioye ſhalbe vpon their heades,<note place="margin">Eſa, 51.3.</note> they ſhall obtayne ioy and gladneſſe. The ſame Prophet alſo ſayth. Surely the Lorde ſhall comforte <hi>Zion,</hi> he ſhal comfort al her deſolations. and he ſhall make her deſert like <hi>Eden,</hi> and her wildernes like the garden of the Lorde, ioye and gladneſſe ſhalbe founde therein,<note place="margin">Iohn. 16.22.</note> prayſe, and the voyce of ſinging. Our ſauiour Chriſt hym ſelfe ſayth. And ye nowe therefore are in ſorrow, but I
<pb facs="tcp:17676:59"/> wil ſée you agayne, &amp; your harts ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, &amp; your ioy ſhall no man take from you. O moſt comfortable reléefe, euen the very deade may be rayſed vp to heare theſe great and comfortable ioyes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are prouided for the Lordes beloued.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> Which ioyes as. S. Paul ſayeth, although our hartes cannot conceiue, yet let our harts beléeue thoſe vnſpeakeable ioyes, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the worthineſſe and excellency of the place be ſuch as we may diſpayre of, in our owne iudgement, becauſe of our great vnworthines, and the multitude of ſinnes: yet if we beléeue that Chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſonne of the liuing God, and that he hath payed the ranſome for our ſinnes, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath nayled our ſinnes to his croſſe, &amp; alſo if we turne vnto him, loue him, and obey him with all our hart, with all our minde, and with all our ſoule, then will he aſſuredly bring vs vnto that place of conſolation, as he ſayeth in Iohn. And though I goe to prepare a place for you,<note place="margin">Iohn, 14 3</note> I will come agayne and receyue you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where I am, there might ye be alſo.<note place="margin">Ma. 19.28.29.</note> Alſo the Euangeliſt Mathewe ſayth. And Ieſus ſayde vnto them, verely I ſay vnto you, that when the ſonne of
<pb facs="tcp:17676:60"/> man ſhal ſit in the throne of his maieſty, ye which followed me in the regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall ſit alſo vpon the twelue thrones and iudge the twelue tribes of Iſraell. And who ſo euer ſhall forſake houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, for my names ſake, he ſhall receiue an hundred folde more, and ſhall inherite euerlaſting life. Theſe wordes are not ſpoken by a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man, who may lye, and deceyue, but they are ſpoken by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſonne of God hym ſelfe, whoſe word ſhal ſtand and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for euer, tyme ſhall not chaunge it, nor age ſhall not weare it out. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore foraſmuch as the nature of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is deſirous to be reſolued, whether wée ſhall know one another after this lyfe. I thought good to anſwere briefely, that as our ſtate ſhalbe farre better, ſo ſhall alſo our knowledge be farre clearer, for in this world we are the more ignoraunt, &amp; our ſences deceyued by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But in the world to come, when we ſhalbe chaunged into an incorruptible eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, then our ſences ſhalbe much more clearer, and we ſhall know farre the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let vs be thus perſwaded, that
<pb facs="tcp:17676:60"/> that worlde is a world of knowledge not of ignoraunce, as our ſauiour Chriſt him ſelfe ſayth vnto the chiefe prieſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would knowe whether he were Chriſt the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God or no? He anſweared, thou haſte ſayde it, neuertheleſſe I ſay vnto you hereafter ſhall ye ſée the ſonne of man ſitting at the right hand of the power of God,<note place="margin">Mat. 26, 24.</note> and comming in the cloudes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which is to no purpoſe that they ſée his ſitting, and his comming, vnleſſe they know it, and yet he ſpeaketh this vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked Iewes that did crucifie him, that they ſhould ſée it, &amp; know it. Much more aſſuredly ſhall the righteous, ſée him and knowe him. The Apoſtle Paul touching this matter ſayth.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> Nowe we ſée through a glaſſe darkely, but then ſhal we ſée face to face, Now I knowe in part, but then ſhall I know euen as I am knowen. So that now what remayneth more comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the godly, and to them that thirſt after Chriſt Ieſu, then to go to a place after this life repleniſhed with all ioye, comforte, conſolation, and euerlaſting lyfe, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which alſo our ſauiour chriſt Ieſus ſhall conducte vs by his mightie power, and in the which is all fulnes of
<pb facs="tcp:17676:61"/> knowledge &amp; perfection of a bleſſed ſtate. The God of all bleſſing and comforte for his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus his ſake, ſpéedely bring vs vnto that celeſtiall ioye, &amp; pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable eſtate. To whome both with the holy ghoſt, be all glory, dominion and power, now and for euer. So be it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A Prayer.</head>
            <p>O Mercifull God, the king of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and gouernour of all thinges, which of thy mercy and goodnes dideſt bring thy people out of Egipt from the bondage of Pharo, and dideſt conducte them through the red ſea, into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable land of Canaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we beſeech thee of thy accuſtomed mercy, deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bondage of ſinne, the tiranny of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and the perſecution of the world, and conduct vs vnto the heauenly Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, the onely Canaan of our euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inheritaunce, where we may raigne in eternall felicitie, with thee and the ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, to whome, both with the holy Ghoſt be all honour and glory now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="exercise">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:61"/>
            <head>A Chriſtian exerciſe for priuate <hi>Housholders.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat doo you chiefely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtianitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the badge of a Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhat is fayth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The verye ſame thing that cannot playnely be expreſſed in wordes, for it is aboue the reach of man, and therfore not vnder the reaſon of man. Howe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, we may giue eche to other intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of it by wordes out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and by the deedes of the godly, which is, that it is the ſéede of aſſured reconciliation, ſowen by God in our heartes, for his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, to ſtirre vs to comfort, and to bind vs to obedience, to giue vs a true certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate in our conſciences, that we are called againe to be the children of God,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:62"/> and that we are ingraffed into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, and to be his members. So that although fayth be ſuch a thing as is giuen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om aboue, as a ſeale of gods mercy. Yet it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red here be low of vs as a talent of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce and knowledge,<note place="margin">Luke. 19.</note> receiued of him to be increaſed by vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth fayth woorke in vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The knowledge of God, the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of our redemption, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of conſcience, through the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let me vnderstand at large your meaning by this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the knowledge of God, we learne that he is our creator, our gouernour, and defender in all neceſſities &amp; daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. And as he hath a ſpeciall care day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to prouide for our bodies, in giuing the plentifulneſſe of the earth, ſo are we perſwaded that he hath a more care for our ſoules, to preſerue them to be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:17676:62"/> ornaments in his heauenly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, by this knowledge, we confeſſe hym to be the Almightie God, to whom all honour ought to be attributed, of thinges in heauen, and thinges in earth, whereby we abandon all Idolatrie and ſuperſtition, as meere inuention of man, and as perſwaſions of Sathan to delude men, and deface the knowledge of the high and mightie God, whom we worſhip, as our maker, and acknowledge to be our defendour, in all euilles, ghoſtly and bodyly.</p>
            <p>By the aſſuraunce of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we are perſwaded that Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus hath payed the ranſome of our ſins, and is the ſufficient ſacrifice to appeaſe gods wrath, and hath for all the church fulfilled the whole lawe, hath vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed death, ſinne, and hel, and hath don all that for vs, which is required of vs, ſo that in hym, God is well pleaſed, and by hym the gats of heauen are opened, and euerlaſting life is promiſed.</p>
            <p>By the conſolation of the conſcience through the holy Ghoſt. We receyue
<pb facs="tcp:17676:63"/> an inward féeling, quickening, and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp of our mindes. That whereas the fleſhe, ſinne, death, and Sathan, do ſéeke dayly to ſuppreſſe vs, and burthen vs with manye miſeries &amp; infirmities, and leade vs euen vnto the gate of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, the holye Ghoſt doth certifie our ſpirite, that we are gods children, he will preſerue vs, that the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why then, fayth is a knowledge and an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuraunce ſent from God to vs, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els? It requireth nothing in vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes. It is a louing conſent and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braſing of the ſame knowledge, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuraunce on our part, yea and doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire in vs a framing of our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable to all thoſe dueties, and ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are expreſſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God, and as do become good Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhat benefite haue you by fayth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By fayth we are iuſtified, that is, we are accepted of God as righteous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:17676:63"/> of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, and ſhalbe reſtored agayne into his fauour, and haue the felowſhip of the bleſſed ſaintes, in euerlaſting ioye, and bliſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If then by faith we are iustified, we neede not good workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fayth onely doth iuſtifie, but this woord <hi>(onelie)</hi> doth not exclude good works. For fayth is not a perfect faith, vnleſſe it be of it ſelfe fuller of good workes, ſo that fayth, and the workes procéeding from that fayth, are not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers but one. As a trée and his twiggs, or lymmes, is but (all) a trée, and ſuch a fayth is accepted, and knowen to God. And yet many deceyue man. For the hippocrite may do good works, and yet haue no fayth, ſo likewiſe fayth it ſelfe, generally is not allowed. For the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelles beléeue, and yet they tremble, &amp; that maketh their fayth to be nothing woorth. Wherefore we muſt neither iudge nor learne faith by imagination, vnleſſe it procéede from the woorde of of God. For that fayth which is ſowen
<pb facs="tcp:17676:64"/> in our hearts by the holy Ghoſt, and watred by the ſame ſpirite, cannot ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as an idle and fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tleſſe trée, but brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth foorth abundance of fruite, for wée may not thinke that the gyftes of the holy ghoſt, (wherof faith is the chiefeſt) are barren, but fruitfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then by your compariſon and meaning, vnleſſe God water the tree which he him ſelfe hath graffed. There is no fruit, ſo that in him is all, and he is all in all, what neede heere anie thing to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are likened to good trées, not too badde, for our capacitie, not for a capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, for in vs there is affection, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and will, which are not in trées, &amp; therefore we ſhould gouerne and direct our ſelues according vnto the rule of fayth. Euen as the ſhip-maiſter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his veſſell on the Seas; let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not the ſhip to runne whether ſhée liſt, but looketh to the North ſtarre, and is guided by the windes, and with all diligence and care auoydeth the ſandes,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:64"/> and the Rockes, and yet all this is in gods handes. And ſo we may reaſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely. God doth ſende vs abundance of Corne and victualls, but we receiue it, order it, and vſe it, or els we maye ſtarue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What good workes be there best knowen, and ſeene in a perfect faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many, both ſpiritual &amp; temporal, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual works, are loue, prayer, patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in affliction, hearing and daylie exerciſing of gods holye woorde, vſing the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſuch lyke. The temporall workes are generally to do good to all men, to giue Almes, to Faſt, to pittie the poore, and helpe their neceſſities, to do equitie and iuſtice, to vſe our ſelues honeſtly, faythfully, and orderly: in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to our Prince, Maieſtrates, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and ſuperiours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then if we haue fayth, we neede no more but to leaue of by the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we haue a good father, it is ynough,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:65"/> but we may not leaue of by the ſame, for as the lyfe of man is not mayntay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by one meale, and as he ought not afterward to be careleſſe for his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, but to haue a care for the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie prouiſion thereof. Euen ſo ſhould he alwayes mayntaine and ſtrengthen fayth, that it might liue vnto lyfe, for in our corrupt nature, it may weaken and ſterue, if the fleſhe, or the enemies reigning in the fleſh, ſhoulde haue the vpper hand. A ſpirituall thing cannot be maintayned with a carnall thing, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be mayntained in a carnall thing, fayth being a ſpirituall thing, may not be mayntayned, neyther with vs, nor of vs, but in vs, and that thing or thinges that are agréeable to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie of fayth, is the ſufficient mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynaunce, our nature is not agréeable to the propertie of fayth, and therefore our nature cannot be the maintenance, and vnleſſe this fayth be maynteyned, it will be ouergrowen, with the wéeds of the fleſh, and ſo wil dye, and then we periſh with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:65"/>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the true maintenaunce of fayth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The exerciſing of gods holy word, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall prayer, and vſing the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How shall we exerciſe gods worde?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not onely by reading it, but by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring learned preachers to expounde it, and not by hearing it expounded, but by vnderſtanding it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is expounded, and not onely by hearing and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it, but afterward by applying and vſing it vnto the honour of God, and our euerlaſting comfort and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How shall we praye?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not with the lipps, but with our hart, not ignorauntly,<note place="margin">1. Co. 14.15</note> but with vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, hauing alwayes in the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of our harte, the ſorrofulneſſe of our ſinne, and the ioyfulneſſe of Gods mercy, ſhaking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one with defiance, neuer to put it on agayne, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb facs="tcp:17676:66"/> the other with affiaunce, alwayes to holde it faſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.1.2.</note> lifting vpp our hartes chéerefully, and beléeuing verely that the Lord doth heare vs when we call vnto hym, and wyll helpe vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>vvhy should we pray continually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 21.36 Ro. 12.11.12 Eph. 6.18.19 Mat. 26.41. 1. Pet 5.8.</note>Becauſe we are ſo commaunded, and for that our enimies do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually hang about vs, and tempt vs, and ſéeke euery day, and euery houre, to bring vs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction both of body and ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Should we pray but for our ſelues onelye, and for none els.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes, we ought to pray one for an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Acts. 7.60. Ex. 23.11. Acts. 12.5. Nu. 47.48.</note> aſwel our enimies as our fréends, that the vertue and force of the prayer which ſhall procéede from the mouth of the godly, may extend aſwell vnto the vngodly for their amendement, as alſo to the oppreſſed, for their eaſe, and alſo to the néedefull for their helpe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ought we to pray for the deade.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:66"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>vvhye?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their eſtate is not ſuch as néedeth our prayers, for God in his ſecret wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, hath elected whom he wyll, and his determination will he not alter, wherefore thoſe which are appoynted to ſaluation, cannot be in better ſtate by our praiers, and thoſe that are damned, can we not redéeme by our praiers, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we will make our praiers of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter force then the blood of Chriſt. The Apoſtle would not haue vs to praye for them that be a liue;<note place="margin">1. Io. 5.16.</note> which do ſinne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, much leſſe for them that be deade. For whoſe ſinnes ſake, they are rewarded with vnbaylable death,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But ſome in ſaying. Lord haue mercie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, or God take him to his mercie, when their freind is deade, do ſay that it hurteth not, but is a word of charitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hurteth, in that it continueth igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the ſpeaker, &amp; giueth a boldnes
<pb facs="tcp:17676:67"/> &amp; yl example to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weaker who in their ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, taketh euery thing for a preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is agréeable to their owne mind, neyther can it be a woord of charity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is fruitleſſe, for charitie ought to haue eyther pittie, remorſe, ayde, or good aſſiſtant action, as féeding the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, clothing the naked, aſſiſting them that want, or ſuch lyke, but this worde helpeth not, neyther aſſiſteth any thyng at all, therefore no charitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How shall we vſe the Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reuerently, penitently, and faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: according to gods inſtitution ſet foorth in his holy word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>vvhat is a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sacrament is the pledge of gods mercy and loue towards vs, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing receyued and vſed of vs reuerently and worthely, is as a comely and decent ornament, to faſhion and ſhape vs to the forme of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How many Sacraments be there?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:67"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>vvhich be they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>vvhat is Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a ſigne of our newe byrth, and regeneration, that as we were concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and borne in ſinne by <hi>Adam,</hi> and continue the courſe of our nature vnto the full age of man, ſo are we new ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in Chriſt, and continue to growe vnto the full age of Chriſt in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and holyneſſe, not that the water in Baptiſme hath the force to do it, but as with water we waſh away the ſpots and filth of our garment, ſo by the holy Ghoſt, whoſe figure the water is, we waſhe our inwarde man from all the corruption of <hi>Adam,</hi> as appartayning to death, and put on the freſh and cleane garment of holineſſe, and newe conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, by the which as God hath made a perpetuall league and couenaunt of
<pb facs="tcp:17676:68"/> his mercy, with man vnder the figure of Circumſition, which repreſented Baptiſme, ſo is there a couenaunt in man, in the which is required fayth, newe obedience, and newe conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the putting off, of the olde man, and putting on of the newe, which is ſhaped in true holineſſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>vvhat benefite haue we by Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt remiſſion of our ſinnes, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the planting of gods grace and all good vertues in vs, thirdely, the vniting of vs into Chriſt, and fourthly our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, as appeareth by theſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſcripture following.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 2.38.</note>
               <hi>Amend your liues, and be Baptized e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of you, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of ſinnes, and ye ſhall receyue the gift of the holye Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.2.</note>
               <hi>By whome alſo wee haue acceſſe through fayth, vnto this grace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:68"/>
            <p>
               <hi>By one ſpirite are we all Baptized into one bodie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.13</note> 
               <hi>whether we be Iewes or Grecians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goe ye into all the worlde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 1.6.6</note> 
               <hi>and preach the Goſpell to euery creature, and he that ſhall beleeue and be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, shall be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is there nothing required of vs in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes, fayth, for it is ſayde, whoſoeuer beléeueth and is baptized, ſhalbe ſaued, and agayne Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth. <hi>Knowe that a man is not iuſtified by the works of the lawe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>but by fayth in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>vvhie then, are Infants Baptized in whom there can be no faith, becauſe they haue not heard the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is neceſſary that Infants ſhoulde be Baptiſed aſſoone as they are borne, becauſe at their firſt entrance, they ſhoulde take poſſeſſion of the Lordes
<pb facs="tcp:17676:69"/> couenaunte which he graunted to our forefathers, and to all the poſteritie yet vnborne, when he gaue the ſigne of Circumſition,<note place="margin">Deut. 29.13</note> which is the ſigne of Baptiſme, vnder which league and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt, all Infantes are enclined, and as they dyd in circumſition, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe Infantes. So in Baptiſme ought we to Baptize Infantes. To whome (as vnto the poſteritie of our forefathers) this couenaunt extended.</p>
            <p>And as touching their fayth, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the ſame the ſeake of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of fayth,<note place="margin">The fayth of Infants.</note> which is as muche to ſay that the ſame ſigne of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition which was a figure of Baptiſme,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> and nowe Baptiſme it ſelfe, was that couenaunt wherein was ſealed the righteouſneſſe of fayth, which in déede worketh from the beginning by grace. In the electe ſecretely, and in ryper yéeres apparauntly, otherwiſe it ſhould be thought, that fayth ſprang from our ſelues, whiche cannot be, leaſt there myght followe an error, that we Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our ſelues, becauſe fayth iuſtifieth. Howe be it in our ſelues we take the
<pb facs="tcp:17676:69"/> better holde thereof, becauſe it is the better ſtrength of lyfe, like good children which eſtéeme the beſt thinges, and leaue the worſt, and direct our ſelues according vnto the ſame. Beſides all this in the innocencie of our infancie, we muſt beléeue touching the very ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie it ſelfe, that the beléeuing pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſanctifieth the childe, which is as much to ſay, that God hath bleſſed the poſteritie of the faythfull, with fayth,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.21.</note> by giuing that figure of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which to all the godly generation,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.15</note> is called the figure of fayth, and if among them any be reprobated as ſome of the godly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that is not vnto vs, but we muſt leaue it vnto God, who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued his ſecret iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to him ſelfe, not acquainting man with it, and yet hath left Chriſt to be the ſwéete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of life, to them that are ſaued,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.22.</note> and the ſauour of death, vnto death. For as in the elected, Chriſt hym ſelfe, is for them faythfull, and by his fayth, God hath ſhewed his righteouſneſſe vnto all and vpon all, ſo is he vnto the reprobate and wicked, the ſauour and taſte of death, vnto death.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:70"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then Baptiſme is nothing worth, but vnto the faithfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, for <hi>Symon</hi> the ſorcerer was Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed,<note place="margin">Acts. 8.21.</note> but becauſe he receiued not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt (which was for lacke of fayth) he was damned</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhat is the Lordes Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a gage of our reſurrection, and a mainteynaunce of that lyfe which is begun in Baptiſme, whereby we féeding by fayth, on the bodie and bloud of Chriſte, receyue a ſtrong nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to eternill lyfe. Or it is the ſound ioyning togeather of the Churche into the body of Chriſt ſpiritually: whereby the head and members may be knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather in vnitie. And this ſupper of the Lorde cannot be a perfect Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without two ſpeciall meanes,
<pb facs="tcp:17676:70"/> whereof the one is the holy Ghoſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in vs effectually, and opening our mindes to ſée the trueth, and féele the conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the participation of Chriſt his death and paſſion. The other is the godly affection in vs,<note place="margin">Fayth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſepe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rated from a godly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Cal. inſtitu. Lib. 3. Cap. 2. Sect, 8.</note> ſanctified by the ſame ſpirite, and directed by a perfect fayth, which worketh thankefully, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably, and penitently, ſtirring in vs a newe continuall conuerſation, which maketh a worthie receyuing. And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this twoo meanes, is added a figure, which is breade and wine, and vnto the bread and wine are added ſimilitudes, and then it is a full Sacrament. And the ſimilituds, as diuers wryters ſaith, doo importe theſe operations, namely Nouriſhment, Vnitie, and Conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; whereof the firſt, which is Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment is this, that as bread &amp; wine do nouriſh and comforte our bodies, ſo the bodye and bloud of Chriſt, do nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and comfort our ſoules.</p>
            <p>The ſimilitude of vnitie is, that as many ſéedes make one lofe, and many Grapes, one Cup of wine, ſo we being many, are vnited as one in Chriſt, and
<pb facs="tcp:17676:71"/> Chriſt in vs, he is our head, and he our members. The thirde ſimilitude, which is conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is this, that as the bread and wine are digeſted and turned into the ſubſtance of our bodies, ſo are wée one fleſh in Chriſt, and Chriſt in vs, as the Apoſtle ſayth. <hi>Now ye are the body of Chriſt, and members for your part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haue you any more to ſay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which is ſpoken, is ſpoken briefely,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> how be it Chriſtianly, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we conclude with this counſell, that for as much as the ſacraments are ordayned of God, and their dignity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of the word of God, we ought to haue them in high eſtimation and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. And for as much as we are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted (from a low) to an high eſtate, and eſtéemed greatly in the fauour of God, by vſing them, we ought with all carefulneſſe and diligence, to embrace them. Which to do, the Lorde giue vs grace, for his ſonne Chriſt his ſake. A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17676:71"/>
            <head>A Prayer.</head>
            <p>VVE ſee and behold our owne eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate (O moſt merciful father) to be very miſerable and lamentable, and we are compaſſed about with manye forcible enimies, which do ſeeke to make it worſe and woorſe, &amp; to bring vs to the vtter ouerthrow of our ſelues, our ſoules and bodies, and to heape a curſe vpon our poſteritie. We are ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, that we are made as the fat Bulles of Baſan, and as the wilde Bores of the wood, ſo that we fall into al filthie con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſation, lewde luſt, abhominable ſin, and diuelliſh deſires, in ſo much that our conſcience is putrified, our heartes are hardened, and our ſoules do faynt, thy word is not eſteemed, thy meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers not regarded, godly exerciſes neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and we are like to periſh, vnleſſe thou O Lord come ſpedely with thine acquainted mercy, &amp; help, for vaine is the help of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fained is the loue of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is quit gone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, truth is bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, &amp; iniquitie rayneth, Iuſtice is per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iured, and falſehood hath taken the regall ſeate. The ſepter of righteouſnes is broken, &amp; our honour is caſt downe
<pb facs="tcp:17676:72"/> to the ground, the gates of hell are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and the floodes of Sathan hath ouerflowen the whole world. We feele no comforte in the ſocietie of man, no ioye in the lyfe of nature, no recreation in the time, for the longer it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the more it is corrupted O Lorde, the very infernall hell flaſheth and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeth his flames, in all the world, the hartes of men are taken priſoners, and their conſciences ſeared. Let vs not O Lorde be partakers with the Infideles leaſt we perish with them. Strengthen vs for our truſt is in thee, and vnder the winges of thy mercy is our refuge, O the comforte of Iacob, &amp; the ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gth of Iſraell, be mercifull vnto thy poore ſtocke of Iaphets, thou haſt not lockte vp thy fauour in Canaan, but diſperſed it in all the worlde. Let not the multitude of our ſinnes drawe thy vengeaunce vnto our confuſion, but let the plentifulnes of thy mercy, draw our ſpeedie reconciliation vnto thee, ſtop our wilfull race O Lorde betimes leaſt we runne headlong to confuſion, beate downe the force of Sathan that
<pb facs="tcp:17676:72"/> he may not haue a dominion ouer vs. And eſtablish vs in thy trueth, that we may haue a comforte in thy woorde, and Sacrament, and ioyfully trauell to the meeting of thy ſweete ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, to receyue with him the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall crowne of glory, in the euerlaſting kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. To the which we humbly beſeech thee to ſend vs all. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
